<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/sri-lestari/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 03:34:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Sri at TEDx Ubud</title>
		<link>/sri-at-tedx-ubud/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 19:16:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tedx Ubud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ubud]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/sri-at-tedx-ubud/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back this spring we let you know Sri Lestari was going to travel from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike for made it to TEDx Ubud.  Sri just shared with us the video of her time at TEDx.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back this spring we let you know Sri Lestari was going to travel from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike for made it to TEDx Ubud.  Sri just shared with us the video of her time at TEDx.</p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/73zCEWpFEu4?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="460" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lestari Is Off to TEDx Ubud</title>
		<link>/sri-lestari-is-off-to-tedx-ubud/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 16:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bali]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[funds raised]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modified]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/sri-lestari-is-off-to-tedx-ubud/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe src="http://www.indiegogo.com/project/365537/widget" width="224px" height="486px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Will Sri Lestari Reach TEDx Ubud on Her Modified Motorbike?</title>
		<link>/will-sri-lestari-reach-tedx-ubud-on-her-modified-motorbike/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 22:23:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disabled]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspiration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[model]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modified motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[paraplegic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social workers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tedx Ubud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UCP Wheels for Humanity]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/will-sri-lestari-reach-tedx-ubud-on-her-modified-motorbike/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last week we shared a photo of Sri Lestari, a social worker who is employed by a Whirlwind partner, UCP Wheels for Humanity, in Yogyakarta, Indonesia.  We found out after our post that she has been asked to speak at the TEDx Ubud conference on June 1st.   Sri is hoping to make her trip to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.indiegogo.com/project/365537/widget" width="224px" height="486px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Last week we shared a photo of Sri Lestari, a social worker who is employed by a Whirlwind partner, <a href="http://www.ucpwfh.org/">UCP Wheels for Humanity</a>, in Yogyakarta, Indonesia.  We found out after our post that she has been asked to speak at the<a href="http://tedxubud.com/"> TEDx Ubud</a> conference on June 1st.   Sri is hoping to make her trip to Ubud a much richer experience by traveling from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike increase awareness and share her experiences with others in the disabled community along the way.</p>
<p>I asked Sri what motivated her to make this trip (almost 750 miles) on motorbike. She responded with the following:</p>
<p><em>“Since I work in UCP Wheels for Humanity 2009, I visit more disable who just stay at home.  They are happy when they see me, because I am disabled, I am a women and I can work. I really want to share my experience how can be life independence and healthy as disabled (paraplegic).<br />
“The campaign really important because disabled in Indonesia still difficult to get out from their houses because no access, especially for public transportation.  My live change since I have modified motorcycle.</em></p>
<p>“Most people didn’t trust me when I told them that I am paraplegia, they surprise I can live independently, go everywhere by myself on the modified motorcycle and can work. When I do social assessment with the paraplegic, at the beginning they don’t believe me, after I talk deeply about paraplegic they are more open, when I told them that I can ride the modified motorcycle they smiling, I am so happy can make them smiling, after that they will contact me regularly and more deeply asking how can be independent specially for our daily live and get a job and they invite me to visit them with my motorcycle.</p>
<p>“Each time there are new paraplegic in my hometown some friends will tell me to visit them, mostly family who has disabled very happy when I visit them. Some of them  are desperate  to support the disabled  to have more spirit, because the disabled  will said that you are not feel what I am feeling, but when I talk to them they won’t refuse me, because I just like them.</p>
<p>“Some Mom who has children with disability said that, they want they children can be like me, even be diffable person but still can work.</p>
<p>“I am happy because I can work n earn money, so I can do home visit to my paraplegia friends in my home town or Yogyakarta in the weekend, share my experience n give them motivation.</p>
<p>“But I also want to share out of my home town and out of Yogyakarta, so that why I really more supported to do the trip.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Shifts into High Gear with International Quality Standards</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-shifts-into-high-gear-with-international-quality-standards/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 20:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expansion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high volume]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[highest quality product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international standards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jogjakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mass production]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QC Systems]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social enterprise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tracking customers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[worldwide]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-shifts-into-high-gear-with-international-quality-standards/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With the 2010 Whirlwind RoughRider® on track to reach more than 20,000 riders next year, the process for ensuring that each chair is of the highest quality becomes an even greater challenge. Unlike Whirlwind’s first 25 years, it is no longer cost-competitive for one person to hand-make every RoughRider from start to finish. Now, as [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure id="attachment_1102" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1102" style="width: 449px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1102 alignright" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-300x200.jpg" alt="Sri Lestari takes her nephew for a ride on her Whirlwind RoughRider® near Jogjakarta, Indonesia." width="449" height="299" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-500x333.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069.jpg 735w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1102" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Sri Lestari takes her nephew for a ride on her Whirlwind RoughRider® near Jogjakarta, Indonesia.</strong></figcaption></figure>
<p>With the 2010 Whirlwind RoughRider® on track to reach more than 20,000 riders next year, the process for ensuring that each chair is of the highest quality becomes an even greater challenge. Unlike Whirlwind’s first 25 years, it is no longer cost-competitive for one person to hand-make every RoughRider from start to finish. Now, as we expand into mass production, Whirlwind and our partners must streamline the production process to create experts in the manufacture of specific wheelchair parts and collaborate to make a great product. Whirlwind’s development of complex quality control systems is emblematic of our transition from a traditional nonprofit to a social enterprise capable of delivering unique, top quality products to tens of thousands of riders in need all over the world.</p>
<p class="Normaltext">Whirlwind is working with our overseas manufacturing facilities, ensuring that design specifications, change processes, and production methods yield the highest quality product possible. To achieve this, the Whirlwind tech team has developed formal processes for controlling quality, managing design changes, and effectively tracking customer complaints to continually improve the RoughRider. International standards guide Whirlwind and our producer-partners to create and implement QC systems effective in managing high-volume, industrial manufacturing applications around the world.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
