<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/updates/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 03:34:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Elder Makes Ancestral Trip to the Amazon in a RoughRider Wheelchair!</title>
		<link>/elder-makes-ancestral-trip-to-the-amazon-in-his-roughrider/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:31:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amazon Jungle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rugged Terrain Wheelchair]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://whirlwindorg.local/?p=3301</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whirlwind was contacted  last summer by Joshua Van Winkle about a wheelchair that could handle the rugged terrain of the Amazon jungle. He was planning an ancestral trip for three generations of families, including an elder gentleman that needed a wheelchair that was sturdy and reliable.  We recently received this thank you letter that touched our hearts. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span class="Apple-converted-space">Whirlwind was contacted  last summer by Joshua Van Winkle about a wheelchair that could handle the rugged terrain of the Amazon jungle. He was planning an ancestral trip for three generations of families, including an elder gentleman that needed a wheelchair that was sturdy and reliable.  We recently received this thank you letter that touched our hearts. We were glad to have been able to help him out to make his extraordinary journey a success!</span></p>
<p><span class="Apple-converted-space"><strong>LETTER WE RECEIVED FROM JOSHUA VAN WINKLE:</strong></span></p>
<p><em>Dear Whirlwind,</em></p>
<div dir="auto">
<div>
<p><em>Last August my friend Ankur Wate (who had trained and worked extensively with a man named Don Cesareo for many years in the jungle) and I planned a group trip down to Secoya territory (and their ancestral homelands near the Ecuador/Peruvian border called Lagarto Cocha) with him.</em></p>
<p><em>Unfortunately Don’s older wheelchair was in poor condition and unable to traverse rough Amazonian terrain for such a trip.</em></p>
<p><em>So Abkur suggested we look around for a wheelchair that would could do such a task. And we found your website online.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div dir="auto">
<div>
<p><em>As all of us that were planning to go on this trip work normal jobs and were by no means financially wealthy, so we wrote to Marc personally asking if he was able to discount the price of a normal Roughrider model so we could afford to get it for Don.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div dir="auto">
<div>
<p><em>Marc was super generous and discounted it for a fair price. So myself and another friend split the cost and brought it down to Ecuador for him as a gift. </em><em>I personally am a custodian with the local school district at the moment, but I, and a group of close friends have a very strong connection with the Secoya people.</em></p>
<p><em>On this particular trip last August, we spent about 2.5 weeks down there to bring together 3 generations of Secoya families together for a special trip to Lagarto Cocha, their ancestral homelands, for time together and traditional ceremonies that the elders have been upholding and practicing since a young age.</em></p>
<p><em>It was a very special trip made possible by Marc and everyone at Whirlwind for making such an awesome wheelchair. </em><em>He had an amazing time as did we all.</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you so much for all of your help and generosity.</em></p>
<p><em>Best regards,</em></p>
<p><em>Joshua Van Winkle</em></p>
<p>We are always happy to hear when the RoughRider has made someone’s ability to travel off the beaten path possible. We look forward to continuing to help more people reach their dreams!</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Morocco Peace Wheels Project</title>
		<link>/morocco-peace-wheels-project/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 05:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://whirlwindorg.local/?p=3262</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After more than two years of extensive e orts, Whirlwind has managed to pull together the key partners for a major wheelchair project in Morocco. The project would support a social enterprise, called Peace Wheels that includes local wheelchair manufacture and assembly of imported RoughRiders® in conjunction with efforts to improve access to wheelchairs throughout [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After more than two years of extensive e orts, Whirlwind has managed to pull together the key partners for a major wheelchair project in Morocco. The project would support a social enterprise, called Peace Wheels that includes local wheelchair manufacture and assembly of imported RoughRiders® in conjunction with efforts to improve access to wheelchairs throughout the country.</p>
<p>The project is the brainchild of Salam Hassan, an Iraqi wheelchair rider and former Whirlwind wheelchair engineer. Salam is a US citizen. His wife Sara Tanzakkine is Moroccan and is a Whirlwind employee.</p>
<p>In September 2017, the project planning team visited Morocco for two weeks to meet with potential partners. We secured collaboration with White Dove, a disabled-run NGO in the northern city of Tetouan, on developing new wheelchair services in Morocco. Whirlwind requires that a local disability organization play a leading role in projects that we support. White Dove currently receives capacity building support from USAID and European Union projects. We contributed a Peace Wheels sports wheelchair and a RoughRider for a wheelchair technology exhibition sponsored by White Dove in Tetouan on Dec. 15, 2017.</p>
<p>The Rotary Club of Casablanca has agreed to purchase more than 300 wheelchairs annually and has expressed interest in collaborating with an American Rotary Club on a joint humanitarian project to meet the wheelchair needs of Moroccans with disabilities. Our partners at the Coalition for Independent Living in Tbilisi, Georgia, whose RoughRider factory is a model for the Moroccan project, will provide assembly line training and quality control to greatly increase the number of wheelchairs produced.</p>
<p>The Entraide Nationale du Maroc is the government agency responsible for purchasing wheelchairs for distribution to persons with disabilities in Morocco and they agreed to purchase 9,000 wheelchairs in 2017. Whirlwind statement with Faoud el Madani, General Director of L’Entraide Nationale, regarding the government’s commercial tender for purchasing wheelchairs and about their willingness to improve the functioning characteristics of the wheelchair specifications for their commercial tenders.</p>
<p>After our meeting, the Entraide Nationale agreed to collaborate on a future assessment survey that will get feedback from users on di erent types and models of wheelchairs. Currently, the government purchases only basic wheelchairs imported from China. One of the Morocco project’s goals will be to educate the government about the need for purchasing wheelchairs, which are appropriate for the rough environment in Morocco and to change the government’s current wheelchair provision policy. White Dove would implement the wheelchair assessment survey and the adoption of World Health Organization guidelines for wheelchair provision services.</p>
<p>USAID/Morocco’s new Democracy and Governance O cer, Jennifer Nikolae , met with our team in September at the US embassy in Rabat and expressed a willingness to administer any project that USAID- Washington would be willing to fund. Agreement of the in-country USAID o ce is a precondition for any USAID support for a disability project.</p>
<p>Whirlwind Wheelchair International wants to express its commitment to supporting and collaborating with<br />
Salam Hassan and Peace Wheels in Marrakesh. Whirlwind has followed Salam’s development in Morocco of a lightweight sports wheelchair and a newly invented hub-less wheelchair, as he begins to develop appropriate technology wheelchairs in Marrakesh, which can be manufactured at a low price from locally available materials with locally trained workers who have disabilities. In addition, we have agreed that Peace Wheels can also be the official distributor of RoughRider wheelchairs in Morocco and North Africa.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congratulations to all the WINNERS of the RoughRider 2017 Best Video &#038; Story Contest!</title>
		<link>/winners-of-the-roughrider-rough-terrain-2017-best-video-story-contest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 17:49:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rough-Terrain Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Winners of the RoughRider Photo/ Video Contest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://whirlwindorg.local/?p=3212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Read about the RoughRider rough-terrain Wheelchair that gets people off the pavement and out into the roads less traveled. Our riders write us from national parks, beaches and even the jungles of the Philippines! When our wheelchairs allow someone to gain a greater sense of independence and freedom, we know that we need to keep [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Read about the RoughRider rough-terrain Wheelchair that gets people off the pavement and out into the roads less traveled. Our riders write us from national parks, beaches and even the jungles of the Philippines!</p>
<p>When our wheelchairs allow someone to gain a greater sense of independence and freedom, we know that we need to keep working and pushing forward to design wheelchairs giving greater freedom and independence through mobility for all!</p>
<p><strong>Eric Logan – <em>WINNER of the ROUGHRIDER BEST PHOTO CONTEST!<br />
</em></strong>Eric’s photo was taken at Surigao del Norte in the Philippines. He won $50 USD OR free push handle extenders for every photo that we used in 2017 and 2018!</p>
<p><em>Here is what Eric had to say about his RoughRider:</em></p>
<p>Dear RoughRider,</p>
<p class="normal"><span lang="EN">I&#8217;m Eric Logan and I love your product! My photo was taken in Surigao del Norte, Philippine on the island of Mindanao.  That&#8217;s where I have used it for everything from a marathon to daily exercise or just getting around where there is no sidewalk.  I like challenging myself, so I look for the biggest hill, or mountain and try to go up and down it several times.  I have used this chair on the ocean bottom (really), where my wife family lives in Surigao. It bumps up against the China Sea, and at low tide, in some places, you can literally walk on the sea floor. You guys have a great chair and really half the world that needs a chair could really use one.</span></p>
<p class="normal"><span lang="EN">Thanks a lot for creating it!</span></p>
<p class="normal"><span lang="EN">Eric Logan</span><span lang="EN"> </span><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3243" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675.jpg" alt="" width="1200" height="675" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675.jpg 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675-500x281.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Alex-Neupauer-All-Terrain-RoughRider-Wheelchair-Arches-National-Park-1200x675-1024x576.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Alex Neupauer – WINNER of the ROUGHRIDER BEST PHOTO CONTEST!</strong><br />
Alex’s photo was taken at Arches National Park in Utah, USA. He won $50 USD PLUS free push handle extenders for the best photo in a US or Canadian state, provincial or national park.<br />
<a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3244" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675.jpg" alt="" width="1200" height="675" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675.jpg 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675-500x281.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Caitlyn-Meyers-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Iceland-1200x675-1024x576.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Caitlin Myers – WINNER of the ROUGHRIDER BEST PHOTO CONTEST!</strong><br />
Caitlin’s photo was taken at Thingvellir National Park in Iceland. She won $200 USD for the best testimonial that was published in 2017 PLUS we donated a RoughRider in her name, manufactured by our partners in Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam to a wheelchair rider in need in that country. In addition, she received a $200 discount on the purchase of a new RoughRider or future product offered.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3245" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675.jpg" alt="" width="1200" height="675" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675.jpg 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675-500x281.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Chris-Daly-All-Terrain-RoughRider-in-Colorado-1200x675-1024x576.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /></a><br />
<strong>Chris Daly– WINNER of the ROUGHRIDER BEST PHOTO CONTEST!</strong><br />
Chris’ photo was taken at Rocky Mountain National Park in Colorado, USA. She won $50 USD OR free push handle extenders for every photo that we used in 2017 or that will be used in 2018!</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OM8oJknmBg4?rel=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><br />
Evan Swarth – WINNER of the ROUGHRIDER BEST VIDEO CONTEST!<br />
Evan’s video was taken at Joshua Tree National Park in California, USA. She won $200 USD for best video PLUS we will be making a donation of a RoughRider wheelchair in her name, manufactured by our partners in Tbilisi, Georgia to a wheelchair rider in need there in addition to a $200 discount on the purchase of a new RoughRider or any of our future products offered!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Alejandro Menéndez Finds Independence and Freedom with his RoughRider Wheelchair</title>
		<link>/rough-terrain-wheelchair-roughrider-mobility-locally-repairable-wheelchair-durable-wheelchair/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alejandro Menéndez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rough-Terrain Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://whirlwindorg.local/?p=2967</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At Whirlwind we love hearing from people whose lives have been changed by the RoughRider wheelchairs we are able to provide for them. When our rugged-terrain wheelchairs allow someone to gain a greater sense of independence and freedom, we know that we need to keep working and pushing forward to help those in need. This [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At Whirlwind we love hearing from people whose lives have been changed by the <a href="/product/roughrider/">RoughRider</a> wheelchairs we are able to provide for them. When our rugged-terrain wheelchairs allow someone to gain a greater sense of independence and freedom, we know that we need to keep working and pushing forward to <a href="/donate/">help those in need</a>.</p>
<p>This is just how we felt when we heard from Alejandro, a Cuban gentleman who shared his story of what life was like before and after receiving his <a href="/product/roughrider/">RoughRider</a>. Prior to an accident that resulted in the amputation of both his legs, Alejandro had lived a very active life style. He struggled with many different types of wheelchairs over the years, unable to accomplish simple, everyday tasks and was dependent on other people to help him with his life. He also emphasized the time, energy and cost that was wasted due to the limitations of other wheelchairs he had owned.  He wrote to tell of his experience after receiving his Roughrider wheelchair, where he expresses how his life has been dramatically changed for the better.</p>
<p><strong>LETTER WE RECEIVED FROM ALEJANDRO:</strong></p>
<p><em>Hola amigos,</em></p>
<p><em>My name is Alejandro D&#8217;Armas Menéndez. I live in Havana, Cuba. I&#8217;m 54 years old. I have a degree in Plastic Arts and Radio Amateur that I received 12 years ago. Both of my legs were amputated, one below and the other above the knee as a result of an automobile accident.  I never really found out, I was unaware of the existence of this company that manufactures wheelchairs before I met you. You came to me by chance.</em></p>
<p><em>About 2 months ago they told me in my health area to pick up a wheelchair that had arrived as a donation, with no more details than that. Prior to the accident, my life was the same as that of an ordinary Cuban. I did physical exercises, I danced, I swam, I walked long distances and did other outdoor activities, I climbed mountains, etc. and others. After the accident, my life became very difficult and complicated, I was dependent on other people for almost everything. In the 25 years that I have been using a wheelchair, my hands have passed over more than 11 different kinds of wheelchairs. </em></p>
<p><em>The limitations to these other wheelchairs are gigantic and horrible,. I suffered a lot because I could not do what I liked the most. It was a lot of work spent many jobs to sit in them from any position, I spent a lot of energy to work or move. To climb or descend simple slopes or sidewalks, I had to be helped by someone. It took up more of my time and resources to repair the chair and make it into something I could use then time that could have been spent on doing things that were more useful.</em></p>
<p><em>The most common issues I experienced were the punctures of the tires. I was very limited because of the adverse conditions and situations that occurred almost daily. I had suffered and suffered so much that I hated the wheelchair I had been using with my whole being. </em></p>
<p><em>One day I went to Havana&#8217;s Malecón and I thought to get rid of the chair I would throw it into the sea!&#8230;For a second I felt like I’d lost my he had lost my mind. I only held back when my conscience awoke and, I recovered. My reason and I did not find my legs.</em></p>
<p><em>Since receiving my RoughRider my life has changed radically. In the same moment that it was taken out of the box and was assembled, I felt an attraction very similar to love at first sight, really. My heart was beating strongly, my hands were sweating. I could smell the sweet the fruit of an unequaled and never before experienced a nervousness like I never known have before. </em></p>
<p><em>Believe me, I do not exaggerate when I share this.</em></p>
<p><em>Now I can move everywhere, including the province of Mayabeque, covering a little more than 60-70 kilometers. With the confidence that I will not suffer from the bitter breakdowns with my chair. Now I can keep my hands cleaner.  My friends are also very happy every time they see me sitting in my Roughrider and with the joy on my face. Now I can go up and down the sidewalks without falling, now I can move regardless of the weather, or the quality of the streets or roads. A few days ago on a slope downhill and in free fall I reached around 10 km / h speed. Never before had I dreamed I could do this much less accomplish.</em></p>
<p><em>I find the Roughrider to be very safe, despite any sudden turns and crazy maneuvers that I oblige it to perform, it maintains it’s balance and stability; its wide rear tires, grip the asphalt very well in an incredible way. It is very light, with less than half the forces used to move in the previous ones. The Roughrider, breaks the inertia; occupies only the necessary space, neither more nor less, without reducing comfort; it even allows me to go through narrow places and tight spaces.</em></p>
<p><em>With my new Roughrider wheelchair I feel the safety, balance and comfort it offers me all at the same time.</em></p>
<p><em>Gracios my amigos,</em></p>
<p><em>Alejandro</em></p>
<p>Hearing from Alejandro and how his life has been changed by receiving a RoughRider wheelchair from Whirlwind is the reason we do the work we do. We look forward to continuing the work we do each day to help more people reach their dream of the freedom and independence they deserve!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Handcycle Trike Update</title>
		<link>/handcycle-trike-update-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 18:19:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aaron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[handily]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[test drive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trike]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/handcycle-trike-update-2/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Aaron taks one last test drive on the handcycle trikes before they are shipped to Indonesia for the trike trial later this month!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span class="full-image-block ssNonEditable"><span class="thumbnail-caption" style="width: 650px;"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1140 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13.jpg" alt="Whirlwind Handcycle Trike Update" width="3264" height="1865" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13.jpg 1920w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13-768x439.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13-500x286.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13-300x171.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Trike-Aug-13-1024x585.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 3264px) 100vw, 3264px" /></a><br />
Aaron taks one last test drive on the handcycle trikes before they are shipped to Indonesia for the trike trial later this month!</span></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lestari Is Off to TEDx Ubud</title>
		<link>/sri-lestari-is-off-to-tedx-ubud/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 16:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bali]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[funds raised]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modified]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/sri-lestari-is-off-to-tedx-ubud/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="http://www.indiegogo.com/project/365537/widget" width="224px" height="486px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Traveler&#8217;s Program Update</title>
		<link>/travelers-program-update/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 19:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fatuma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jireh Childern's Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Masake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TRaveller's Program]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uganda]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/travelers-program-update/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Fatuma before and after receiving her new RoughRider Wheelchair in Masake, Uganda We recently received this post from Craig Pierson on Facebook “This Summer a group of us went to Masaka, Uganda to build a playground at Jireh Children&#8217;s Center. While there we met Fatuma. As you can see her wheelchair was in pretty rough [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><span class="full-image-block ssNonEditable"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Fatima.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1098 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Fatima.jpeg" alt="Fatuma before and after receiving her new RoughRider Wheelchair in Masake, Uganda" width="432" height="216" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Fatima.jpeg 432w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Fatima-300x150.jpeg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 432px) 100vw, 432px" /></a></span></strong></p>
<p><strong><span class="full-image-block ssNonEditable"><span class="thumbnail-caption" style="width: 432px;">Fatuma before and after receiving her new RoughRider Wheelchair in Masake, Uganda</span></span></strong></p>
<p>We recently received this post from Craig Pierson on Facebook “This Summer a group of us went to Masaka, Uganda to build a playground at Jireh Children&#8217;s Center. While there we met Fatuma. As you can see her wheelchair was in pretty rough shape. When we came back to the States I started a quest to find her a wheelchair that would better suit her needs with the rough terrain of Uganda. Here is her old wheelchair, and here is her new wheel chair. The smile tells it all.. — at Jireh Childern&#8217;s Center, Masake, Uganda.” Craig used <a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/programs/">Whirlwind&#8217;s Traveler&#8217;s program</a> to bring Fatuma a RoughRider.</p>
<p>Thanks for sharing Craig we are glad she is enjoying her RoughRider!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>RoughRider Technical Support Pages Launched!</title>
		<link>/roughrider-technical-support-pages-launched/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 19:14:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[launched]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Questions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technical Support]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/roughrider-technical-support-pages-launched/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Have a technical support question about your RoughRider? Now it’s easy to find.  Whirlwind Wheelchair just launched our RoughRider Technical Support pages.  We’ve started with the basics – assembly and adjustment – but will be adding more; so check back and let us know if there is something you would like us to include.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-177" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2.jpg" alt="Will Wrist Band Will Power" width="1200" height="427" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2.jpg 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2-768x273.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2-500x178.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2-300x107.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/04/will_wrist_band2-1024x364.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /></a></p>
<p>Have a technical support question about your RoughRider? Now it’s easy to find.  Whirlwind Wheelchair just launched our <a href="/roughrider-support/">RoughRider Technical Support pages</a>.  We’ve started with the basics – assembly and adjustment – but will be adding more; so check back and let us know if there is something you would like us to include.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thanks for Visiting us at the International Seating Symposium</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-wheelchair-at-the-international-seating-symposium/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 22:25:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International Seating Symposium]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marc Krizak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matt McCambridge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/thanks-for-visiting-us-at-the-international-seating-symposium/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; Whirlwind Product Development Director, Matt McCambridge and Executive Director, Marc Krizak this week at the International Seating Symposium. Great event &#8211; RSTCE!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1104 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2.jpg" alt="Executive Director Marc Krizack and Matt McCambridge at the International Seating Symposium" width="4000" height="3000" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2.jpg 1920w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2-500x375.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MMMK-at-ISS_2-1024x768.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 4000px) 100vw, 4000px" /></a></strong></p>
<p>Whirlwind Product Development Director, <em>Matt McCambridge</em> and Executive Director, <em>Marc Krizak</em> this week at the International Seating Symposium. Great event &#8211; RSTCE!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Demo RoughRider Available at Riekes Center</title>
		<link>/demo-roughrider-riekes-center/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2013 21:36:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Updates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[All-Terrain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[demo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Palo Alto]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Riekes Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/demo-roughrider-available-at-riekes-center/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; Hey there Bay Area – Wondering if the RoughRider is right for you?  Now you can find out!  The Riekes Center in Palo Alto has a 17” demo RoughRider available to check-out, just ask to speak to Sharon.  Try it out and see if it’s right for you!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Demo-chair.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-1156 alignleft" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Demo-chair-300x214.jpg" alt="???????" width="409" height="292" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Demo-chair-300x214.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Demo-chair.jpg 448w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Hey there Bay Area – Wondering if the RoughRider is right for you?  Now you can find out!  The Riekes Center in Palo Alto has a 17” demo RoughRider available to check-out, just ask to speak to Sharon.  Try it out and see if it’s right for you!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
