<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/whirlwind-wheelchair/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 22:02:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Elementary Students Raise over $5,000 for Whirlwind in Wheels of Hope Activity</title>
		<link>/elementary-students-raise-over-5000-for-whirlwind-in-wheels-of-hope-activity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 16:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[All-Terrain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Colorado]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Denver]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fundraising]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indian Ridge Elementary School]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[project based learning activity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wheel chair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheels of Hope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind Wheelchair]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/elementary-students-raise-over-5000-for-whirlwind-in-wheels-of-hope-activity/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Fourth grade students selling sundaes to raise funds for their Wheels of Hope project for Whirlwind Wheelchair Fourth grade students selling sundaes to raise funds for their Wheels of Hope project for Whirlwind Wheelchair. In fall 2012, 100 fourth grade students from Indian Ridge Elementary School in the Cherry Creek school district of metro Denver, Colorado [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1111" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids-300x168.jpg" alt=" Fourth grade students selling sundaes to raise funds for their Wheels of Hope project for Whirlwind Wheelchair" width="505" height="283" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids-500x281.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids-1024x575.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Wheels-of-Hope-kids.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 505px) 100vw, 505px" /></a></p>
<p><em>Fourth grade students selling sundaes to raise funds for their Wheels of Hope project for Whirlwind Wheelchair</em></p>
<p class="MsoNormal"><span class="full-image-block ssNonEditable"><span class="thumbnail-caption" style="width: 700px;">Fourth grade students selling sundaes to raise funds for their Wheels of Hope project for Whirlwind Wheelchair. </span></span>In fall 2012, 100 fourth grade students from Indian Ridge Elementary School in the Cherry Creek school district of metro Denver, Colorado began raising funds for Whirlwind Wheelchair International as part of a project-based learning activity. The fourth graders chose Whirlwind Wheel International because of our mission to provide independent mobility to wheelchair riders in the developing world.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>They particularly liked the RoughRider’s unique design, extremely effective on all-terrain, and affordability. Past projects they have supported include: One Laptop per Child, the U.S. Forest Service’s restoration efforts in a large Colorado burn area, and water wells and ready-to-use therapeutic food in Niger, used in the treatment of children suffering of malnutrition. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span></p>
<p class="MsoNormal"><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"> </span>Donna Shepherd, a fourth grade teacher at Indian Ridge spearheading the activity, says, “I use project-based learning to teach economics, research, writing, logic, civics, social studies, etc. in an across-the-curriculum approach to learning. I find that integrating curriculum is a powerful way to make learning meaningful and relevant to students.”<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>She has found project-based learning enrichers their learning experience.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>“Often students come back years later and tell me that it was one of the most important experiences that they remember from elementary school. It is also a fun way to learn.”</p>
<p class="MsoNormal">This year the students’ goal is to raise $20,000 through ice cream Sunday fundraisers.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>As of the end of January, Indian Ridge Students have raised $5,000 for Whirlwind Wheelchair.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Children’s Chairs in Haiti</title>
		<link>/childrens-chairs-in-haiti/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 22:02:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Children's Wheelchairs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haiti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haiti Project]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matt McCambridge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walkabout Foundation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind Wheelchair]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/childrens-chairs-in-haiti/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The need for children’s wheelchairs in Haiti is great.  Our contacts on the ground tell us that even with all the aid pouring in there’s very little for kids with disabilities. Vladimir, who meets Ralf, Whirlwind’s founder, in this video about our Haiti project in the summer of 2010, lost his mother and sustained a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p class="p1">The need for children’s wheelchairs in Haiti is great.  Our contacts on the ground tell us that even with all the aid pouring in there’s very little for kids with disabilities.</p>
<p class="p4"><span class="s2">Vladimir, who meets Ralf, Whirlwind’s founder, in this video about our Haiti project in the summer of 2010, lost his mother and sustained a spinal cord injury in the earthquake. We encountered other kids who were injured in the earthquake, and others who have been struggling for years with disabilities like cerebral palsy and need additional postural support in their wheelchairs.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="Haiti Relief with Whirlwind Wheechair and the Walkabout Foundation" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nJQJ8pMsEcI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p class="p6"><span class="s2">For the past year, Matt McCambridge, Whirlwind’s new Manager of Product Development, has been developing a unique, rugged, pediatric chair that meets postural support needs. We are devoted to developing high-quality low-cost chairs for kids so that they have a safe, reliable means of getting to school and play even in the roughest of conditions.</span></p>
<p class="p6"><span class="s2">In the best of times, there are scant resources available for these kids. Your donation will help fund the final development, manufacture, shipment, and custom adjustment of 250 wheelchairs for kids like Vladimir and others who need our new supportive chair. Please join us in our project to change the lives of children in Haiti through your tax-deductible contribution.</span></p>
<p class="p6"><span class="s2"> </span></p>
<p>[/fusion_text][/fusion_builder_column][/fusion_builder_row][/fusion_builder_container]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
