<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/ralf-hotchkiss/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:52:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>2021 Annual Newsletter</title>
		<link>/2021-annual-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 02:21:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Newsletters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workshop]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9558</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Safety First, Second and Third Solar Power Tricycle Development Wheelchairs to Oglala Lakota Amputees Next Version of the Electric RoughRider Letter from a Grateful Recipient of the Frank Barham Memorial Fund Kellogg Racial Equity Challenge 2030 Dear Friends and Supporters, During 2021, Whirlwind returned to its roots of assisting small-scale RoughRider wheelchair factories, which we [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#safety">Safety First, Second and Third</a></li><li><a href="#tanzania">Solar Power Tricycle Development</a></li><li><a href="#lakota">Wheelchairs to Oglala Lakota Amputees</a></li><li><a href="#electric">Next Version of the Electric RoughRider</a></li><li><a href="#letter">Letter from a Grateful Recipient of the Frank Barham Memorial Fund</a></li><li><a href="#kellogg">Kellogg Racial Equity Challenge 2030</a></li></ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Dear Friends and Supporters,</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-thumbnail"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile.jpeg"><img decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-150x150.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-9559" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-150x150.jpeg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-100x100.jpeg 100w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /></a></figure></div>



<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span>During 2021, Whirlwind returned to its roots of assisting small-scale RoughRider wheelchair factories, which we helped to establish during the last 40 years. Some of these smaller RoughRider businesses did not survive because of local economic conditions, management issues and the lack of support from their Ministries of Health, which preferred to purchase $90-$100 institutional wheelchairs from China’s megafactories through government tenders. </p>



<p>The economic survival of these small wheelchair businesses depends on convincing local buyers that the RoughRider wheelchair, which is made with mild steel, will last 15 years in harsh living conditions and is cheaply repairable with bicycle parts and at local welding shops. However, many of the riders who have some money prefer the light-weight sports wheelchairs with flashy colors and modern detailing, while the families and individuals who are poor take the free wheelchairs distributed by international charities and churches, regardless of the quality and repairability of the free wheelchairs. These are two of the reasons for small RoughRider businesses not having enough customers to keep their businesses economically viable.</p>



<p>In order to keep these businesses alive by selling their wheelchairs, many of our partners need to improve the quality of their RoughRider. Therefore, Whirlwind has started providing technical assistance to 3 RoughRider wheelchair businesses: the ARSOBO factory in Nogales, Mexico, the Fundación Bertha O. De Osete I.A.P.<br>factory located in San Juan del Río, Querétaro, México, and the KIFAS factory in Ankara, Turkey. Whirlwind<br>has asked the two RoughRider businesses in Mexico to send us their wheelchairs, which will be analyzed by Ralf Hotchkiss and Levan Talakhadze for their production quality and for recommendations on how to improve the production quality control in each factory. Salam Hassan, a wheelchair designer, volunteered to help Ken Erickson, owner/manager of the KIFAS factory in Turkey, restart his wheelchair production after closure during the Covid quarantine and the loss of his senior welder. Salam was sent in December by Whirlwind to KIFAS to help improve the welding fixtures for their RoughRider, improve quality control, and to train their new Iraqi welder.</p>



<p>Another important development in 2021 has been our recent attempt to create a low cost, full power electric RoughRider using new hub motor technology from China. We were not happy with our first attempt, which was implemented 10 years ago in the Republic of Georgia, because the older hub motor technology was heavy and required frequent repairs. As you will see in this newsletter, we are cautiously optimistic about our prototype efforts in collaboration with NIOION TECHNOLOGIES CO., LTD, which is based in Jiangsu, China.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, Peter Pfaelzer, cofounder of Whirlwind died in 2021. Peter was fundamental to the development and success of Whirlwind. We will miss his spirit, ingenuity and persistence in pursuing our goals. Finally, we want to thank all of our friends and generous supporters who share our values in a well designed, highly functional and locally repairable RoughRider wheelchair, which has become the best wheelchair for the worst conditions</p>



<p>we encounter as we go out into the world. Whirlwind is committed to always improving the functionality of our RoughRider so that even more people will experience the joy of being alive and realizing their best dreams in the beauty of the world outdoors for themselves, their children and for their elderly relatives. Please help us to continue helping others live their life as fully as possible in this world and with as much happiness as possible.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-left"><span style="font-weight: 400;">With gratitude,&nbsp;</span></p>



<p class="has-text-align-left"><img decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-5712 alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png" alt="" width="300" height="102" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-768x261.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-500x170.png 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature.png 900w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br><strong>Bruce Curtis<br><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chairperson of the Board of Directors</span></em></strong></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-vivid-red-background-color has-background" href="/donate/" style="border-radius:11px"><strong>MAKE A DONATION NOW</strong></a></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots" id="safety"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><b><a id="recipients"></a>Safety First, Second and Third</b></h2>



<p>When Whirlwind was formed in 1980, it was well known that many wheelchair riders got hurt (some seriously) when they rode outdoors. I had a 24-year history of falling once or twice a year, either forward or backward. With the forward falls came broken bones; with the backward falls, concussions. Ralph Nader, with whom I had worked on safety issues through the 1970s, urged earnest attention to the grave dangers of wheelchair design. Ralph Nader’s input, and his support, continues to this day. And I, along with my fellow riders and designers in Whirlwind’s network, am dead serious about designing our chairs to be as stable and safe as they can possibly be.<br>By 1990 we had greatly increased the strength of our chairs, making the common failures of critical parts a thing of the past. Safety First! Backward tipping, unfortunately, was still as bad as ever. It seemed that every solution we created brought problems to other aspects of how the wheelchair functioned.</p>



<p>But Whirlwind’s cofounder, Peter Pfaelzer, gave Whirlwind a challenge that has kept us busy ever since. Our group had lost its focus; we were trying to solve too many problems at once. Peter proposed that we first learn as much as possible about when, and why wheelchairs fail. We knew from experience that injuries to wheelchair riders were quite common. But little was known about whether the incidents and the injuries came primarily from tips and falls, from chairs breaking down, or from other factors.</p>



<p>Because so many active people ride (and crash) their wheelchairs in the San Francisco Bay Area, we found it easy to learn from them how and why these crashes occur, and what injuries resulted. A Whirlwind team led by Ronny Gall spread the word in the community that we were looking for wheelchair riders who had crashed their chairs. Of the 252 incidents that we found, most, 42%, were tips or falls, while 33% were chair equipment failures. The riders in 27% of the incidents required medical treatment. 13 riders (5%) required hospitalization.</p>



<p>The most common injuries came from tips and falls, either in the forward or the backward direction. Forward falls damage more people, so we chose to concentrate on forward falls. This concentrated work paid off with the much longer wheelbase of the RoughRider. Now the RoughRider has virtually no forward tipping problem. Second major Safety Problem solved!</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-medium"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="281" height="300" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web-281x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9567" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web-281x300.jpg 281w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web-959x1024.jpg 959w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web-768x820.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web-500x534.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Ralf-1970-anti-tip-web.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 281px) 100vw, 281px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>That leaves us with the problem of backwards falls. Whirlwind and others have struggled to eliminate the problem of backwards tipping by using wheelie bars. Some worked quite well, but all shared a common problem: wheelie bars stick out behind, getting in the way when the chair and its rider need to be pulled up or bounced down stairs.<br>By the 1970s, I had a wheelie bar that was easily folded up and put out of the way. However, one day I was trying to get into the New York subway when a strong person offered to bounce me down the stairs. All went well until we reached the bottom of the stairs. I thanked him heartily, gave a strong forward push to my chair, and my head fell backward onto the solid concrete.</p>



<p>Needless to say we changed our design criteria immediately. From that day forward any retractable wheelie bar was required to re-deploy itself, by itself, before the chair could safely roll forward again.<br>Such a wheelie bar must be light, cheap and very safe. I have built several and some work well, but not yet well enough. If we can solve this retractable wheelie bar problem, we will have Safety First, Safety Second, and Safety Third!</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots" id="tanzania"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><b><a id="grandmother"></a>Do You Want To Help This Start Up Mobility Business In Tanzania?</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span></h2>



<p>Archy Gomba, Founder and Director of the Shirati for Active Rehabilitation and Development Organization (SARDO), aims to promote the social and economic inclusion of people with disabilities into all aspects of life in Tanzania. As an adult with a physical disability, an arm amputated below the elbow, Archy grew up understanding how disability can create barriers to getting an education, getting a job or being accepted in the community. During the summer of 2019, Archy was invited to participate in the Professional Fellowship Program on Inclusive Disability Employment, which was supported by: U.S. Department of State, Association of University Centers on Disabilities (AUCD); ICI-UMass Boston; and by Humanity &amp; Inclusion. This professional fellowship supported Archy during his five weeks of residencies in different States, where he learned about disability rights, small business development and employment inclusion.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="827" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web-827x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9565" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web-827x1024.jpg 827w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web-242x300.jpg 242w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web-768x951.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web-500x619.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/solartricycle-web.jpg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 827px) 100vw, 827px" /></a></figure>



<p>Whirlwind met Archy while he was visiting Berkeley, California and learning about: local and international disability organizations; disability inclusive community support services; adaptive sports programs; as well as small shop wheelchair manufacturing. In the summer of 2019, Whirlwind provided Archy with a RoughRider wheelchair to take back to Tanzania with him, since he wanted to learn how to set up a RoughRider wheelchair workshop in his home village. After returning home and getting married, Archy saw the need to create a business, which makes and sells solar powered and handcycle tricycles, which would greatly help local persons who have limited mobility become more independent and be able to start a business or get an education.</p>



<p>So Archy developed a prototype of a solar powered electric tricycle, using locally available parts from friends. With a little technical assistance from Whirlwind, Archy successfully created in his workshop a solar tricycle prototype, using 26 inch bicycle wheels, including: an iron chassis, a 15W solar panel, a 24V motor and lithium batteries. Parts that were locally available from friends in Tanzania cost him $299, not including labor or the solar panel.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="790" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web-1024x790.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9566" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web-1024x790.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web-300x232.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web-768x593.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web-500x386.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DORKA-web.jpg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>In addition, Archy has created a handcycle tricycle, which is less expensive, in order to meet the mobility needs of persons with disabilities who do not have much money. Local people have been watching as he constructed his prototypes of solar powered and handcycle tricycles and many people have said that they wanted to buy one. Archy has identified the parts that he wants to purchase from China in order to make larger quantities of these solar tricycles for sale and he wants to expand his workshop business in order to begin selling handcycle and solar powered tricycles and to be able to sell his tricycles in other cities. If you wish to financially or mechanically help Archy finish his prototypes and go to the next stage of of his business by making larger quantities of these tricycles for sale, please contact him:</p>



<p><br>Archy E. Gomba<br>Shirati, Kabwana, P. O. Box 9, Rorya-Mara, Tanzania<br>Phone: +255-75-849-7292<br>Email: archygo@gmail.com</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="lakota"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">RoughRider Wheelchairs to Oglala Lakota Amputees</h2>



<p>During the last week of July 2021, Whirlwind sent a RoughRider wheelchair to Mike Black Elk, who is a single amputee and a client of the Oglala Sioux Tribal (OST) Vocational Rehabilitation Services on Pine Ridge Reservation, South Dakota. On August 2, another RoughRider wheelchair was sent to Kevin Poor Bear, who is a double amputee and also a client of the OST Vocational Rehabilitation Services.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="819" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web-819x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-9564" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web-819x1024.jpeg 819w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web-240x300.jpeg 240w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web-768x960.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web-500x625.jpeg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/jim-warner-web.jpeg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 819px) 100vw, 819px" /></a><figcaption><em>Jim Warne at the OST&nbsp;</em><br><em>Vocational Rehabilitation Office&nbsp;</em><br><em>on Pine Ridge Reservation</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>Jim Warne, photographed with one of the Roughrider wheelchairs that he helped Whirlwind donate to the OST Vocational Rehabilitation Office, also helped the University of South Dakota to establish the Oyate` Circle, a Tribal College Disability Center. The Oyate’ Circle is a resource, education, outreach and training effort that serves Native Americans with disabilities in South Dakota. Led by Oglala Lakota tribal member Jim Warne and named after the Lakota word for “the people,” the Oyate’ Circle conducts education and outreach campaigns about the needs of Native Americans with disabilities. It also offers resources and training for tribal communities and informs them about programs and opportunities available through the center and other agencies.</p>



<p>Both wheelchairs were sent free of charge to Mike and Kevin by Whirlwind due to a generous gift from the widow of Frank Barham, a wheelchair user who was accidentally killed on the highway by a semi-truck while conducting a RoughRider wheelchair fundraising campaign outside of Atlanta, Georgia. Upon receiving Adriana Barham’s donation, Whirlwind set up a Frank Barham Memorial Fund to subsidize RoughRider wheelchairs for Americans who were unable to purchase one for themselves or their family members. These two wheelchairs are the last of 25 RoughRider wheelchairs, which were subsidized by the Frank Barham Memorial Fund and distributed to low-income individuals in the United States from 2019 to 2021.</p>



<p>Whirlwind is hoping to receive additional funding to continue sending RoughRider wheelchairs to Native Americans who need a rugged outdoor wheelchair, which can easily travel over the difficult environments in which they live and can be easily repaired with locally available welding and bicycle parts. The RoughRider wheelchair has been distributed in over 60 countries across the world because of its ability to move easily through mud, grass, snow, uneven streets, and cobblestones without tipping over.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="electric"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Next Electric RoughRider Wheelchair</strong></h2>



<p>Whirlwind and the Coalition for Independent Living created an electric RoughRider wheelchair in 2014 in the Republic of Georgia by using electric bicycle technology from China. Since 2014, the Government of Georgia has purchased 275 electric RoughRider wheelchairs and distributed them throughout Georgia. However, this electric bicycle technology was 10 years old and was not constructed with high-quality components, which required the Georgian Wheelchair Workshop to modify and improve this technology. Currently, their electric RoughRiders have been free of working problems for one year of use.</p>



<p>From this Georgian experience, Whirlwind now understands that in order to successfully use electric bicycle technology for electric wheelchairs in developing countries, we need to identify hub-motors and electronics, which will work reliably over several years without any breakdowns or modifications.</p>



<p>Whirlwind proceeded to identify a business in China, NIOION TECHNOLOGIES CO., LTD, which had experience with power wheelchairs and power add-on technology and we asked if they would be willing to help us to adapt their electronics to a Roughrider wheelchair. The President of NIOION, Avery Liu, enthusiastically identified a hub motor, controller, joystick and lithium battery and Whirlwind purchased a RoughRider wheelchair from the CLASP warehouse in Shanghai for NIOION to use for their prototype development in their facilities.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9563" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors-500x375.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/24inch-wheels-with-hub-motors.jpg 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>Avery assembled the components onto his RoughRider wheelchair and shared a small video of the working prototype. These components are now being shipped to Ralf Hotchkiss and will be assembled onto a RoughRider wheelchair and tested for durability and mobility performance. After Ralf has determined that the hub motors and electronics work successfully and reliably over several months, Whirlwind will be shipping a 2nd set of hub motors and components to the ARSOBO RoughRider factory in Nogales, Mexico for them to prototype and possibly sell locally in the Mexican market. The ARSOBO manager said that they have received several inquiries from local individuals who want to purchase an electric wheelchair. Whirlwind will send a 3rd set of hub motors and components to the RoughRider factory in the Republic of Georgia for them to test locally and a 4th set of hub motors and components to the KIFAS RoughRider factory in Turkey. Hopefully, we will be successful with our electric RoughRider 2 prototype and Whirlwind can begin exploring how to expand the availability of a low-cost, foldable, lightweight, electric RoughRider wheelchair through the CLASP business network.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="letter"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Letter From a Grateful Recipient of the Frank Barham Memorial Fund</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-medium"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Sarah-Meg.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="225" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Sarah-Meg-300x225.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9561" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Sarah-Meg-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Sarah-Meg-500x375.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Sarah-Meg.jpg 720w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>Nine months ago, your organization helped me by giving me a RoughRider wheelchair for a price I could afford on my low income. I live full time in a camper van out in nature and I wasn’t able to get around on the rough terrain that I live on with my walker or a standard wheelchair and I can’t go very far with my crutches. My life was very limited and although I could look at nature every day from my van, I could not easily explore it. Since I got my Whirlwind RoughRider wheelchair, I have learned to wheelchair “hike” with it. I have taken it on lots of trails and I’m getting really good at traversing difficult terrain.</p>



<p>Last week I was lucky to be able to visit the Acadia National Park in Maine. The scenery was breathtaking! And because I had my RoughRider wheelchair, I was able to go “hiking” and see the scenery up close! Here is a picture of me sitting next to Jordan Pond in my Whirlwind wheelchair! Your organization made this experience possible for me and I am immensely grateful! Thank you so much for the amazing work you do getting us disabled folks out into nature. I can never thank you enough for the amazing experiences I’ve had “hiking” in my chair over the last 9 months. You are all amazing! Keep up the good work!</p>



<p>With love and gratitude,<br>Sarah Meg</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="kellogg"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Kellogg Racial Equity Challenge 2030</h2>



<p>In 2020, the W.K. Kellogg Racial Equity Challenge 2030 announced that it was offering $90 million to help build and scale actionable ideas for transformative change in the systems and institutions that uphold racial inequities. Whirlwind was invited to join a consortium of 6 organizations, Arizona Sonora Border Project for Inclusion (ARSOBO), University of Arizona Sonoran Center for Excellence in Disabilities, Warrior Society Development, LLC, Oyate Circle, University of South Dakota, Center for Disabilities, Whirlwind Wheelchair International, Bio-mechatronics Group, Center for Extreme Bionics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Hanger Prosthetics &amp; Orthotics), which proposed a 5-year project.</p>



<p>The project would be carried out by Redefining American Indigenous Disability Inclusion Equity Now and Tomorrow (RAIDIENT), a reservation-based social enterprise focused on disabilities and employment inequities. RAIDIENT’s vision is to reduce Native American disability inequities by establishing four Native American social-enterprises that would address disability health technologies and services for over thirty Tribal Nations.</p>



<p>We proposed to train and hire Tribal members with disabilities to build for others the medical devices they use themselves. The RAIDIENT team includes disability advocates and Native Americans with disabilities who would use their cultural heritage and professional expertise to promote community development for Native American Tribes. RAIDIENT would “on-the-job” train Native Americans with Disabilities on Tribal Reservations to implement professional services including RoughRider wheelchair assembly, wheelchair repair and modification, customized prosthetic/orthotic fabrication, hearing aid distribution, diabetes management and amputation prevention programs.</p>



<p>Sadly, our consortium of 6 organizations was not successful and was not included in the final selection of 10 projects. However, ARSOBO is continuing to work with the Salt River Pima-Maricopa Indian Reservation in Arizona in order to provide low cost hearing aids and RoughRider wheelchairs and Whirlwind has donated two RoughRider wheelchairs to Lakota amputees living on the Pine Ridge Reservation in South Dakota.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2020 Annual Newsletter</title>
		<link>/2020-annual-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 22:02:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Newsletters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workshop]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9576</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pilgrimage of the Camino de Santiago A Request from HCBH hospital in Haiti Whirlwind: What Can Come Next? Designing 21st Century Vehicles For Persons With Disabilities A Request from Fort Larned National Historic Site Dear Friends and Supporters, It is now December 2020, eight months since the beginning of the COVID-19 lockdown. The sale and [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#pilgrimage">Pilgrimage of the Camino de Santiago</a></li><li><a href="#haiti">A Request from HCBH hospital in Haiti</a></li><li><a href="#next">Whirlwind: What Can Come Next?</a></li><li><a href="#vehicle">Designing 21st Century Vehicles For Persons With Disabilities</a></li><li><a href="#larned">A Request from Fort Larned National Historic Site</a></li></ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Dear Friends and Supporters,</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-thumbnail"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-150x150.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-9559" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-150x150.jpeg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/bruce-profile-100x100.jpeg 100w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>It is now December 2020, eight months since the beginning of the COVID-19 lockdown. The sale and distribution of Whirlwind Wheelchairs is on hold. As the quarantine began in April, Whirlwind staff decided to take a furlough, while doing our best to answer requests for wheelchairs and technical assistance.</p>



<p>Because of the severe shortage of protective face masks early in the pandemic, Contra Costa County offered Whirlwind a large number of N95 masks to give out to persons with disabilities. Whirlwind had hoped to distribute the masks through the numerous local disability organizations. Unfortunately, most disability organizations had closed their doors, so we are still looking for ways to distribute these masks.</p>



<p>Starting in 2019, Whirlwind began providing low-cost, subsidized Roughrider wheelchairs to persons on low fixed incomes. This was made possible by a generous $25,000 grant from the Frank Barham family. We have provided subsidized wheelchairs to 15 individuals so far.</p>



<p>Ralf Hotchkiss, Whirlwind’s founder and member of our board, worked early this year at ARSOBO, the Roughrider Wheelchair factory in Nogales, Mexico. Dr. Burris Duncan and Kiko Trujillo of ARSOBO have expressed interest in manufacturing an electric Roughrider with assistance offered by the engineering department of the University of Arizona. Whirlwind is sending ARSOBO a new model electric Roughrider from the Coalition for Independent Living factory in Tbilisi, Georgia. ARSOBO will examine and test this chair in hopes of optimizing it for their manufacture and use in rural Mexico.</p>



<p>In our 2020 annual newsletter, we are including stories from Whirlwind riders around the world. The cover story features a disability organization whose members had tried to push wheelchair riders up the extremely steep pathways of an ancient pilgrimage in Galicia, northwest Spain. The goal of the pilgrimage is to honor the apostle St. James the Great in the cathedral of Santiago de Compostela. Another story is revealed in a request for replacement parts by two Haitian Roughrider owners. Both received their chairs from Whirlwind 5 years ago after their catastrophic earthquake.</p>



<p>Whirlwind needs any amount of financial donations that you can provide to help us survive the COVID-19 quarantine lockdown. Even though our operational costs are low, Whirlwind’s income has been greatly reduced. No one knows if or when the economy will return to normal and many donors have changed their priorities in order to deal with the problems of COVID-19.</p>



<p>All contributions to keep Whirlwind alive and operating are greatly appreciated!</p>



<p class="has-text-align-left"><span style="font-weight: 400;">With gratitude,&nbsp;</span></p>



<p class="has-text-align-left"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-5712 alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png" alt="" width="300" height="102" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-768x261.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-500x170.png 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature.png 900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br><strong>Bruce Curtis<br><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chairperson of the Board of Directors</span></em></strong></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-vivid-red-background-color has-background" href="/donate/" style="border-radius:11px"><strong>MAKE A DONATION NOW</strong></a></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots" id="pilgrimage"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><b><a id="recipients"></a>Pilgrimage of the Camino de Santiago</b></h2>



<p>My name is María Ángeles Iñiguez and I am writing on behalf of the AMIF (Association of People with Physical Disability). AMIF is an association of the city of Villena (Alicante-Spain) and it is dedicated to assist physically disabled persons.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9579" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-1024x576.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-1536x865.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago-500x281.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/caminodesantiago.jpg 1828w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>In October 2015, we attempted to make the Pilgrimage of the <em>Camino de Santiago</em> to realize the dreams of a group of people, that due to their physical disabilities and without the helping of our volunteers, had never lived this experience.</p>



<p>This amazing experience, which was unimaginable for most disabled persons, has been the motive for planning another way. But, to do it we purchased 5 RoughRider wheelchairs from FUNDACION BERTHA O DE OSETE in Mexico.</p>



<p>After a long and arduous process of talking with customs and drug agency officials, we only had to talk to the Pope and the King, we were able to get the RoughRider wheelchairs out of the Spain customs. I think we got the certificate for being tired.</p>



<p>We completed a stage on the Camino de Santiago from Roncesvalles to Logroño, without speaking! We are always in contact with the local police, as that year the <em>Policía Foral de Navarra</em> were with us for almost the whole time.</p>



<p>Firstly, when the couple of policemen introduced themselves to us, they told us they could stay with us for only one day because they had other things to do, however it didn’t happen that way. The second day of walking toward Pamplona, we called the police to communicate that we were starting to walk and they told us that they would be waiting for us at a crossroads, which would lead to a road accessible to our group. But the police were not there, so we followed the signs and those signs led us to the ancient road, Camino de Santiago. It was an old mountain side path that became so narrow, that we couldn’t go back. We could only continue very carefully because on one side we had the wall of the mountain but on the other side we had nothing but moss on the path edge, and if we would step on the moss, we would slip. There was even a moment where our volunteers had to lift up each wheelchair with the person sitting in it. When we got to the end of the mountain path the police were waiting for us, surprised to see that we had passed through with the wheelchairs. From that day on they became our Guardians and I think they won´t forget us and we won´t forget that day either.</p>



<p>In October 2019, we did another stage of the <em>Camino de Santiago</em>, this time from Logroño to Burgos. Unfortunately, this year 2020, we won´t be able to do another stage due to Covid 19 and until the situation is calmer, we prefer to postpone until next year. I hope so. We have more people/partners interested in coming with us: either to travel or to enjoy the walks in the fields that we do every month. We also participate in the San Silvestre Vallecana; as well as a Marathon for people with intellectual disabilities; or in the walk for the integration of people with disabilities.</p>



<p>As you can see, we are making the most of the RoughRider wheelchairs and are proud to be able to bring out smiles and of course we always enjoy our people becoming part of our family.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots" id="haiti"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><b><a id="grandmother"></a>A Request from HCBH hospital in Haiti</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"></span></h2>



<p>Hello Whirlwind,</p>



<p>I am messaging from HCBH hospital in Haiti. We have 4 RoughRider wheelchair users who need some replacement parts. We need main wheel bearings for 4 wheelchairs, plus 3 new pairs of front wheels, the worst of which is coming apart. These parts are for very active guys (you can see them at work making a table) who have enjoyed their RoughRider wheelchairs for 4 years. They look after them so well but the physical material on the front wheels need replacing.&nbsp;&#8212; <em>Rob Dalton</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9581" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh-500x375.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/haiti-hcbh.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><em>Ralf Hotchkiss responded:</em></p>



<p>You need to research local hardware stores or motorcycle shops to identify if they have the following size bearing available to purchase: Bearing#6202 (15mm inside diameter &#8211; 35mm outside diameter &#8211; 11mm thick). This is a common bearing available worldwide, which is why it was selected for use in the hub bearings and front wheel bearings on the RoughRider wheelchair. This #6202 bearing usually has a long life but it will only work for 1 to 2 years in the rough conditions of Haiti near the sea. I am speaking with a local bearing manufacturer in Oakland, California about making an improved version with a longer life, possibly up to 5 years.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In your photographs, there is a lot of rust on the frame and forks and to maintain the strength of the metal, they need to be sanded down and repainted to protect the metal from corrosive salt water and other chemicals in the Haiti dirt/mud. Use steel wool or sandpaper to sand down the rust on all of the metal and after sanding it down, use a spray can of rust reformer paint to protect the metal. If you cannot find rust reformer paint, use the common red primer, which is available almost everywhere.</p>



<p>The conditions of the roads and dirt paths in Haiti are extreme for wearing out the rubber on the front wheels. We suggest new front Zimbabwe wheels for each person plus a backup replacement pair. Therefore, we will send you 16 Zimbabwe wheels with axles/bearings. We are hoping that you will be able to find replacement tires for the back wheels in Haiti? They are available at bicycle shops, which carry 24-inch tires.</p>



<p>Wow! What amazing advice and what an incredible offer of the Zimbabwe wheels! Harold (a very active user I see every day) just had his front left wheel snap off yesterday and is very upset. The RoughRider wheelchair is literally the best physical possession he has and his lifeline to the world. This is amazing news. I will hunt for the wheel bearings; those measurements will prove invaluable! We also have sandpaper and red oxide rust paint to apply when changing them. SO grateful for your help!</p>



<p>Regarding the back wheels, one RoughRider user here (Fritz, the carpenter in the photos) has replaced his back tires with mountain bike style tires and they work great.</p>



<p><em>(Whirlwind sent 16 Zimbabwe wheels, new spokes, 32 bearings #6202, hand-packed at Whirlwind with 80% grease, instead of the normal 40% grease, for a longer life.)</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="next"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Whirlwind Wheelchair: What Can Come Next?</h2>



<p>We stay committed to working with members of the Whirlwind Network to appraise and improve the Whirlwind Roughrider. We are striving toward independent mobility, further and further away from the beaten track. We need the best of chairs for the worst of conditions.</p>



<p>The pandemic has made it harder to exchange new ideas with our network &#8211; travel is out of the question. But some of Whirlwind’s best collaborators are taking advantage of the quarantine and trying out inventions for which they had no time before. Among these are some who have invented critical aspects of Whirlwind’s chairs for over 40 years! We just hope that all in our network, along with our families, come out on the other side healthy and strong.</p>



<p>Our latest Roughrider is designed for use both indoors and outdoors. It is exceptionally strong, but no heavier than a standard wheelchair. This chair is buildable and repairable with tools and materials that are available throughout most of the world. But while the Whirlwind is more mobile than most wheelchairs, there are places where it is too slow, too hard to push, or where it simply cannot go. We do have potential solutions for some of these problems, but can we make these solutions practical?</p>



<p><strong>WASTED ENERGY</strong></p>



<p>A lot of the rider’s energy is wasted trying to push a wheelchair over paths that are tilted for drainage. The weight on the front wheels pulls them down the slope, the front wheels turn to the side and the chair veers off the trail. To force the front wheels to turn back up the slope the rider must drag one hand on its hand-rim. This is like riding with the brakes on. More than half of the rider’s energy is often taken just to keep the front of the chair from being pulled down into the gutter.</p>



<p>A chair will roll in a straight line along-side slopes if it has very little weight on the front wheels. Some riders reduce the weight on their front wheels by moving their rear wheels to a position further forward on the chair. They ride their chairs very easily, regardless of side slopes. They also tip over backwards easily, especially when they climb hills.</p>



<p>The rear wheels can be safely moved forward, thus nearly eliminating downhill turning, if a flexible wheelie bar is installed on the back of the chair. We hope that we can design a wheelie bar that functions very well, yet still is cheap, light and simple.</p>



<p>A wheelie bar unfortunately blocks the way when the chair and its rider are being pulled backwards upstairs. When the chair rolls away from the stairs, the wheelie bar must be re-deployed to keep the chair from tipping backwards. This re-deployment must be automatic, yet purely mechanical.</p>



<p><strong>POWER BOOST</strong></p>



<p>Many wheelchair riders can push easily over flat floors, but they lack the strength and endurance to go very far outdoors. They don’t want the cost and weight that come with full power wheelchairs; they just need a little push.</p>



<p>The tip of a well-designed wheelie bar could serve as an excellent mounting point for a single motorized wheel. The rider could travel quickly while still pushing as hard as was comfortable on their hand-rims. They would still get the exercise they need. The harder they could push on their hand-rims, the farther they could go and the lighter and cheaper their battery could be.</p>



<p>We are happiest when we have the input of the experts we know. They are wheelchair riders, welders, bicycle builders, engineers, artists and business people, women and men, very young and very old. We need the wisdom of anyone from anywhere who has the interest to observe and create; the more diverse the network the better.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The best of chair for the worst of conditions!</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="vehicle"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Designing 21st Century Vehicles For Persons With Disabilities</h2>



<p>The Merlin Prize for accessible, autonomous, electric vehicles (A2EV) is a crowd-sourced design competition to generate innovative and inclusive transportation solutions for people with physical, sensory, and/or cognitive disabilities. Automotive industry experts predict that electric vehicles (EVs) will surpass the number of gas-powered vehicles on the road in the coming decades, and virtually all autonomous vehicles are electric. The goal of this challenge is to make autonomous, electric vehicles accessible for all.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-scaled.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="483" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-1024x483.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9582" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-1024x483.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-300x141.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-768x362.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-1536x724.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-2048x966.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-500x236.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/merlin-ev-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>Whirlwind Board members Ralf Hotchkiss and Bruce Curtis were contacted by the Merlin Mobility Foundation and invited to speak with Lawrence Williams, the founder of Merlin Mobility and President of the Merlin Mobility Foundation. Mr. Williams explained his interest and reasons for creating the Merlin Prize Challenge and invited both of us to participate as judges. The 16 judges were asked to identify their 1st, 2nd and 3rd place choices from the engineering design submissions of individuals, as well as, from organizations. After lengthy discussion among all of the judges and based on the total scores received by individual judges, the three Merlin Prize Challenge winners were identified. However, everyone was in agreement that no one had submitted a design proposal for an accessible electric automobile, which was ready for commercial production.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots" id="larned"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A Request from Fort Larned National Historic Site</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-medium"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger-225x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9583" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger-225x300.jpg 225w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger-768x1024.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger-500x667.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/fort-larned-ranger.jpg 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>When Fort Larned National Historic Site built a new parking lot in 2013, getting to the Visitor Center became a much longer walk over historic ground. In other words, visitors cannot access the historic buildings or the Visitor Center in a vehicle. We have visitors daily who don’t mind the quarter mile walk. But there are plenty of visitors who are not able to walk for various health reasons. Many are elderly, yet still yearning to learn about our history.</p>



<p>The Roughrider wheelchair has been used by appreciative visitors for about 6 years. It solves the problem of visitors who need a wheelchair, which sometimes happens daily. The visitors and staff are dependent on having the wheelchair. It is still in good condition except the back and seat upholstery are worn out. Do you have replacement parts so we can get it fixed up this winter?</p>



<p><em>George Elmore</em><br>Chief Ranger<br>Fort Larned NHS</p>



<p><em>Whirlwind responded:</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p>We are sending you a 2-inch seat tube extender that is already attached to your new seat fabric, which you will screw into the existing holes on the 14-inch seat tubes. You just need to unscrew the screws holding the seat fabric, take out the long thin metal form inside the seat fabric seam edge. Then insert the long thin metal form inside the seat fabric seam edge of the new seat fabric and screw the seat fabric into the frame with the screws.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the new back rest fabric, you will need to pull the push handles off of the back of the chair before you pull the backrest fabric over the backrest tubes. Please use boiling hot water in two, 1/2-gallon plastic containers, and put both push handles while still attached to the back rest tubes into the hot water for about one minute. Then you can pull off the plastic push handles. Pull the back fabric over the backrest tubes and reattach the push handles with crazy glue.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2019 Annual Newsletter</title>
		<link>/2019-annual-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:34:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Newsletters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workshop]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=5711</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Letter from the Chairperson Responses from Recent RoughRider Recipients A RoughRider for an Indigenous Grandmother One World Project in Morocco Subsidized Wheelchairs from the Frank Barham Fund]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#letter">Letter from the Chairperson</a></li><li><a href="#recipients">Responses from Recent RoughRider Recipients</a></li><li><a href="#grandmother">A RoughRider for an Indigenous Grandmother</a></li><li><a href="#morocco">One World Project in Morocco</a></li><li><a href="#barham">Subsidized Wheelchairs from the Frank Barham Fund</a></li></ul>



<h2><b><a id="letter"></a>Whirlwind Goes Back To Our Roots</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-2793" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/BruceCurtis-150x150.jpg" alt="Bruce Curtis" width="150" height="150" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/BruceCurtis-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/03/BruceCurtis-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/03/BruceCurtis-100x100.jpg 100w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/03/BruceCurtis.jpg 400w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" />With the holiday season approaching, we would like to thank all of you whose contributions have helped give hope and support to so many people around the world this past year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As many of you are aware, Whirlwind has undergone many changes in 2019, including the retirement of the Executive Director, Marc Krizack, and the addition of its original Founder and Chief Engineer, Ralf Hotchkiss to</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">the Board of Directors. These changes have resulted in a new direction and challenge for the work Whirlwind will be undertaking in 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ralf’s original vision included helping to develop small metal-shops that are capable of manufacturing the Roughrider wheelchair, using hand tool technology and standard bicycle parts, while also providing local wheelchair repair, modifications and employment for persons with disabilities to manufacture, repair and modify wheelchairs.</span></p>
<h3><b>Recent Wheelchair Market Trends</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since the early 2000s, almost all of the major wheelchair makers in the world are currently making their wheelchairs in large factories in China. Many of the small wheelchair making businesses in developing countries, which also employed wheelchair users as workers, went out of business in the last 15 years because they were unable to sell their wheelchairs for a commercial price after religious and humanitarian charities donated thousands of free wheelchairs into their countries. That immense flood of chairs bankrupted local wheelchair businesses, and also eliminated the local wheelchair repair services, as the economics of fixing those factory chairs no longer made sense.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In today&#8217;s world, some wheelchair users in developing countries are receiving higher quality wheelchairs through free international donations but they cannot find any wheelchair repair services to sustain the active life of their wheelchair and after 1-3 years are desperately searching for a replacement wheelchair.</span></p>
<h3><b>A New Chapter</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After 15 years of successful work manufacturing the RoughRider in a modern Chinese factory, in order to provide large quantities of wheelchairs for international distribution, Whirlwind has witnessed the benefits of quality production jigs and quality control inspection in order to produce thousands of reliable and safe wheelchair. Therefore, we are now revisiting the original vision of promoting and sustaining small-scale wheelchair businesses with new and valuable perspectives about how to upgrade and improve their production jigs and the importance of&nbsp; training staff to conduct quality control inspections.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whirlwind wants to offer the small RoughRider manufacturers our newest design of the RoughRider wheelchair, including new seat and back upholstery and the handbrake design. In order to increase the active life of all RoughRider wheelchairs, Whirlwind wants to update their understanding of the importance of using sealed bearings, aluminum hubs and rims, as well as how and where to purchase quality parts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beginning in 2020, Whirlwind will begin to provide technical assistance to the surviving small RoughRider manufacturers/businesses in developing countries and help them to:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Update earlier models of the Roughrider wheelchair to the latest design</span></em></li>
<li><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Improve the existing welding jigs</span></em></li>
<li><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Source raw materials and repair parts at the best quality &amp; lowest price</span></em></li>
<li><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Train staff to evaluate each wheelchair user according to WHO wheelchair provision guidelines</span></em></li>
</ul>
<h3><b>Whirlwind Needs Your Support!</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whirlwind creates and supports </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wheelchair Ecosystems</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. We make small-scale wheelchair businesses possible, with a wheelchair product that provides daily mobility to people who might not have any other opportunity to leave their home.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We would like to invite you to join us by making a very generous contribution this holiday season to help us implement our goals of <strong>helping wheelchair users to stay active</strong> and working in their communities around the world.&nbsp;</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your donation also helps Whirlwind to <strong>promote and support small businesses</strong>, which employ wheelchair users, while also <strong>providing local wheelchair repair services</strong> and modifications.</span></p>
<h3><b>Purchasing RoughRiders Helps Us Too!</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another way you can help us would be to consider <a href="/product/roughrider/">purchasing a RoughRider wheelchair</a> for an elderly parent or a relative or even a friend who could benefit from having a way to go outside and enjoy the world. </span><b><i>The profits from each Roughrider wheelchair sold on our website directly funds Whirlwind’s operating budget, they are as crucial to our survival as traditional donations!</i></b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Much of what we are trying to accomplish will take time, and with your support, you are helping Whirlwind to change the lives of so many people all over the world. I hope you will join us to help expand our reach and influence into the new year.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">With gratitude,&nbsp;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-5712 alignnone" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png" alt="" width="300" height="102" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-300x102.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-768x261.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature-500x170.png 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/bruce-signature.png 900w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><br><strong>Bruce Curtis<br><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chairperson of the Board of Directors</span></em></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-background has-vivid-red-background-color" href="/donate/" style="border-radius:11px"><strong>MAKE A DONATION NOW</strong></a></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots"/>



<h2><b><a id="recipients"></a>Stories From RoughRider Recipients</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Christina Rodriguez, who lives on Pico Island in the Azores Islands of Portugal recently purchased a Roughrider wheelchair to continue her daily walks with her 75-year-old husband who has Parkinson’s. </span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We do need the wheelchair quite urgently …my husband still walks a bit but without the wheelchair there is no way we can go out every day as we try to …and it would be a shame.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Deanna Welka in memory of her father:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">“My father is in a hospice and we have been taking him outside, along a gravel path beside a creek, in a regular wheelchair …needless to say we broke the wheelchair. This led me to think that a donation of a gravel and grass friendly wheelchair to the hospice in my father’s memory, might be a useful gift for other families who wish to take their loved ones farther afield to enjoy nature.”</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Alejandro D’Armas Menéndez, a double amputee in Havana, Cuba:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Since receiving my RoughRider my life has changed radically. In the same moment that it was taken out of the box and was assembled, I felt an attraction very similar to love at first sight, really. My heart was beating strongly, my hands were sweating. I could smell the sweet fruit of an unequaled [gift], and… experienced a nervousness like I [have] never known before.&#8221;</span></i></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&nbsp;From Caitlyn Meyers in Iceland:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’ve now had my RoughRider for a couple years and it continues to give me access to parts of my life that I thought I would never get back… I rounded a corner of the steep path along Þingvellir Iceland,</span></i> <i><span style="font-weight: 400;">on this most recent trip, guiding my chair around obstacles, and suddenly saw an entire waterfall that I hadn’t known existed. On our honeymoon, I’d had to stop at the top of that path because I knew my legs wouldn’t carry me. I feel so grateful for what my RoughRider has given me and how much more I can accomplish now.</span></i></p>
</blockquote>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-text-color has-background has-very-dark-gray-background-color has-very-dark-gray-color is-style-dots"/>



<h2><b><a id="grandmother"></a>A RoughRider for an Indigenous Grandmother</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In July, Whirlwind received a request to provide a RoughRider wheelchair for Grandmother Agnes Baker Pilgrim (95yrs) in support of her work as Chief Spokesperson for the</span><a href="http://www.grandmotherscouncil.org/who-we-are"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">International Council of 13 Indigenous Grandmothers</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-5720 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim.jpg" alt="" width="852" height="852" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim.jpg 852w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim-768x768.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim-500x500.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/agnespilgrim-100x100.jpg 100w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 852px) 100vw, 852px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Grandmother Agnes had two common hospital transport wheelchairs, which did not move easily over the grass or gravel and were very difficult to use in rural or dirt environments. Her daughter Nadine (69yrs) would push her wheelchair whenever Agnes was traveling internationally to attend important events.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whirlwind received a donation from</span><a href="https://plenty.org/"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Plenty International</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for the cost of the wheelchair, which would make it much easier for Nadine to push Grandmother Agnes over the rough terrain they encountered during their international travels, and with a frame that is strong enough to survive rough handling by airplanes and taxis and which can be easily and cheaply repaired by using local welding shops or standard bicycle parts.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whirlwind&#8217;s Chairperson, Bruce Curtis, and Levan Talakhadze, a wheelchair technician certified by the World Health Organization to evaluate wheelchair users, drove from Berkeley, California to the home of Grandmother Agnes in Grants Pass, Oregon in October 2019 to deliver the Roughrider wheelchair. Levan adjusted the length of the footrests and the height of the armrest for her to be comfortable and attached a push handle extender, which would make it easier for her daughter Nadine to push the wheelchair with one hand. Levan also provided some simple explanations for how to use the wheelchair going down the ramp or across her front lawn. Agnes said that it was the very first time she had traveled over her front lawn.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sadly, we recently received notice that Grandmother Agnes had died on November 27, 2019, just one month after receiving her new wheelchair. Whirlwind has sent an email expressing our sadness at her passing and encouraging her daughter Nadine, to donate Grandmother Agnes&#8217;s Roughrider wheelchair to another indigenous grandmother or someone else in her tribe.</span></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots"/>



<h2><b><a id="morocco"></a>One World Project in Morocco</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During September and October 2019, Whirlwind’s Bruce Curtis and Salam Hassan provided technical assistance and supervision in Morocco, as disability consultants to the International Research And Exchange Board (IREX), in order to implement a 12-month project in 4 Provinces of Morocco, Beni Mellel, Draa’a, Marrakesh and Tetouan, with IREX’s Moroccan disability partners, the disability NGO </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">White Dove</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and the social enterprise </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Peace Wheels</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. IREX’s Morocco project will educate local wheelchair users, DPOs, government officials and media journalists about the need for buying different models of wheelchairs and for the provision of wheelchairs according to WHO Basic guidelines.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_5735" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5735" style="width: 1024px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-5735 size-large" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-1024x695.jpeg" alt="" width="1024" height="695" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-1024x695.jpeg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-300x204.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-768x521.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-1536x1043.jpeg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-2048x1390.jpeg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-500x339.jpeg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0998-scaled.jpeg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-5735" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Hayat El Machfou learning how to do a wheelie, instructed by Salam Hassan</em></figcaption></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hayat El Machfou, Vice President of the Moroccan Parliament of Morocco, accepted our invitation to participate in the 1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">st</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Wheelchair Skills Training Camp, which was held in Marrakesh from September 9-14, 2019.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hayat</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> El Machfou,</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> who had polio when she was young, uses crutches and a wheelchair, and wanted to improve her wheelchair skills. She participated in all 5 days of the 1</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">st</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Wheelchair Skills Training Camp and received a certificate of completion. She also received one of the active wheelchairs, purchased by IREX&#8217;s One World Project through USAID&#8217;s CLASP Program, as did most of the wheelchair users who participated in the Camp.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_5736" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5736" style="width: 1024px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-large wp-image-5736" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" width="1024" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-300x225.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-768x576.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-2048x1536.jpeg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-500x375.jpeg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_0973-scaled.jpeg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-5736" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Tomasz Tasiemski PhD, with training participants</em></figcaption></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tomasz Tasiemski PhD, a Master Trainer who uses a wheelchair and is the Dean of the Active Rehabilitation Department at the University of Poznan, Poland, implemented the wheelchair skills training for 19 participants from 4 provinces.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The wheelchair users participated each day in a wheelchair comparison and evaluation research study, which was translated into Arabic and the data was entered into a database. Tomasz believes he will be able to write and publish an article in a professional journal about the participants‘ evaluation of the 5 different models of wheelchairs.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_5737" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5737" style="width: 1024px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-large wp-image-5737" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-1024x584.jpeg" alt="" width="1024" height="584" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-1024x584.jpeg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-300x171.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-768x438.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-1536x876.jpeg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-2048x1168.jpeg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-500x285.jpeg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG_1233-scaled.jpeg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-5737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Training Graduates with Tomasz Tasiemski, Bruce Curtis and Salam Hassan</em></figcaption></figure>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-dots"/>



<h2><b><a id="barham"></a>Frank Barham Memorial Fund</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 2018, Whirlwind <a href="/the-frank-barham-memorial-fund/">received a generous donation</a> of $25,000 from the widow of Frank Barham, to provide subsidized Roughrider wheelchairs to individuals who could not afford to pay the full price. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So far, in 2019, Whirlwind has shipped subsidized Roughriders to wheelchair users in New Mexico, California, Massachusetts, Colorado, Missouri and Montana.</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jeffrey Wasilowski, a recent double amputee, had only a broken wheelchair.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">James Sharp, receives a small social security check, and loves camping outdoors.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">LaRae Gallegos, living on Social Security, was in a car accident five years ago and her wheelchair does not work well in the Montana environment.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whirlwind will continue providing subsidized Roughriders as we get requests from individuals who cannot afford the full price. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Please consider <a href="/donate/">making a donation</a> in support of Whirlwind providing subsidized Roughriders for Americans who are living on a fixed income and cannot afford to purchase a Roughrider wheelchair.</span></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-background has-vivid-red-background-color" href="/donate/"><strong>CONTRIBUTE TO SUBSIDIZED WHEELCHAIRS</strong></a></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PBS NewsHour With Jim Lehrer</title>
		<link>/pbs-newshour-with-jim-lehrer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 22:05:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[durable wheelchairs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Earthquake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Haiti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[January]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Leher]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[low cost]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PBS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PBS NewsHour]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco State]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/?p=328</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[PBS NewsHour covers Whirlwind Wheelchair International&#8217;s efforts to send low-cost durable wheelchairs to Haiti for amputees after the January 2010 earthquake Ralf Hotchkiss, is speaking the former headquarters at SFSU. Transcription for this video:  Whirlwind Wheelchair on PBS NewsHour with Jim Lehrer reported by Spencer Michels]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe loading="lazy" width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xi770ZEvhAM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>PBS NewsHour covers Whirlwind Wheelchair International&#8217;s efforts to send low-cost durable wheelchairs to Haiti for amputees after the January 2010 earthquake Ralf Hotchkiss, is speaking the former headquarters at SFSU.</p>
<p>Transcription for this video: <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Whirlwind-Wheelchair-on-PBS-NewsHour-with-Jim-Lehrer-reported-by-Spencer-Michels.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i> Whirlwind Wheelchair on PBS NewsHour with Jim Lehrer reported by Spencer Michels</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Makes the RoughRider a Different Kind of Wheelchair? (Part I)</title>
		<link>/what-makes-the-roughrider-a-different-kind-of-wheelchair-part-i/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 21:20:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rugged]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/what-makes-the-roughrider-a-different-kind-of-wheelchair-part-i/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whirlwind Wheelchair puts users in the center of the design process.&#160; As such, the RoughRider has evolved out of the most common user needs we found.&#160; This is the first installment in a series that highlights some of the design features that make the RoughRider a dynamic chair. So what makes the RoughRider a different [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Whirlwind Wheelchair puts users in the center of the design process.&nbsp; As such, the RoughRider has evolved out of the most common user needs we found.&nbsp; This is the first installment in a series that highlights some of the design features that make the RoughRider a dynamic chair.</p>



<p>So what makes the RoughRider a different kind of wheelchair? Solid&nbsp;flexible all rubber front caster wheels- Whirlwind&#8217;s co-founder Ralf Hotchkiss talks about what makes the USA RoughRider&#8217;s rear tires stand out against the competition.</p>



<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9nq7xRAmNXg?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>



<p>Transcription for this video:&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/What-Makes-the-RoughRider-a-Different-Kind-of-Wheelchair.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i> What Makes the RoughRider a Different Kind of Wheelchair</a></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years</title>
		<link>/i-havent-tipped-once-in-the-10-years/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 19:50:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[KGO radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tip Resistant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/i-havent-tipped-once-in-the-10-years/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; Whirlwind’s co-founder, Ralf Hotchkiss was interviewed in December by San Francisco’s KGO radio. Check out the audio clip and find out why he hasn’t tipped forward out of his RoughRider’s® in ten years! Transcription for this video: I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uMtWLhIqs7s?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Whirlwind’s co-founder, Ralf Hotchkiss was interviewed in December by San Francisco’s KGO radio.<br />
Check out the audio clip and find out why he hasn’t tipped forward out of his RoughRider’s® in ten years!</p>
<p><strong>Transcription for this video</strong>: <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/I-Haven’t-Tipped-Once-in-the-10-Years.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i>I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whirlwind&#8217;s Handcycle Tricycle Development and Testing</title>
		<link>/whirlwinds-handcycle-tricycle-development-and-testing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 21:47:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amherst]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ayuba Gufwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bob Cann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chinandega]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[collaboration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Creativity Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial support]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hampshire College]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hand Cycle Tricycle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hand-crank propulsion method]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nicaragua]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prototesting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ramos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USAID]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchairs for Nigeria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[worldwide]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwinds-handcycle-tricycle-development-and-testing/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Many types of hand-powered tricycles are used by people with disabilities around the world, from lightweight sports handcycles for racing and recreation to rolling stores to cargo trikes loaded with merchandise. Whirlwind is applying our experience with wheelchair propulsion, ergonomics, and manufacturing to the development of a cargo handcycle that can be efficiently produced at [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many types of hand-powered tricycles are used by people with disabilities around the world, from lightweight sports handcycles for racing and recreation to rolling stores to cargo trikes loaded with merchandise. Whirlwind is applying our experience with wheelchair propulsion, ergonomics, and manufacturing to the development of a cargo handcycle that can be efficiently produced at large scale, compactly shipped around the world, and be affordably and easily maintained in the smallest workshops. We are developing this product with financial support from USAID and in collaboration with our network of wheelchair builders, riders, service providers, and colleges and universities throughout the world.</p>
<p>San Francisco State University and Santa Clara University student interns have contributed to our project research by talking with tricycle riders and builders to gain a better understanding of how people are using handcycle tricycles both for personal mobility and as platforms for mobile businesses.</p>
<p>Ayuba Gufwan, the founder of Wheelchairs for Nigeria, visited Whirlwind this fall to talk about his experiences building and riding handcycle tricycles in Nigeria. He observed, “There is so much poverty, and the trikes help people to get around and provide for their families. There is a whole range of activities that the trikes can solve.”</p>
<p><strong>Tricycle Prototype Testing in Nicaragua</strong></p>
<p>Whirlwind began this project by exploring how different, well-proven designs from around the globe perform when transported to new environments. Working with Whirlwind, Donna Cohn and Bob Cann at the Creativity Center at Hampshire College in Amherst, Massachusetts built a prototype rear-wheel-drive tricycle, similar to the style that is popular throughout India. In August, Whirlwind founder Ralf Hotchkiss and Professor Cohn took this tricycle to Nicaragua to test the prototype with six trike riders in Chinandega, home of long-time Whirlwind collaborator Thelma Ramos.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-2310 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-300x171.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="171" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-300x171.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-500x285.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-768x438.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-200x114.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-400x228.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-600x343.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n-800x457.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/01/26993797_10156151954468750_7906205434224764454_n.jpg 960w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>Having explored many options, Whirlwind’s tech team is now moving forward with a simple and versatile design appropriate to multiple environments. The first handcycle that Whirlwind will put into production will be a hand-cranked, front-wheel-drive trike, similar to those proven throughout East Africa, but with the added ability to push directly on the rear wheels, like on a wheelchair. The bicycle-style, hand-crank propulsion method is comfortable for efficient longer distance travel at higher speeds, while the rear-wheel push rims give the rider increased maneuverability in tight spaces and on rough or steep terrain where it may be too difficult to use the hand crank.</p>
<p>Whirlwind has designed the handcycle trike to be a platform adaptable to the needs of the riders and communities where the trike will be used. Whirlwind will offer standard options for configuring trikes for hauling cargo, selling goods, or just getting around. We will collaborate with wheelchair builders around the world to develop custom add-ons and design improvements. We will also use the Internet to share a library of open-source, tricycle-related products and accessories available worldwide.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Diverse &#8211; October 2011</title>
		<link>/diverse-october-2011/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2011 20:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fabrication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Improving]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco State]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Teaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair Designs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/?p=483</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss teaches a wheelchair design and fabrication class at San Francisco State University and enlists the help of students in continually improving wheelchair designs for the developing world.  Read The Story Here.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ralf Hotchkiss teaches a wheelchair design and fabrication class at San Francisco State University and enlists the help of students in continually improving wheelchair designs for the developing world.  <a href="http://diverseeducation.com/article/16515/">Read The Story Here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mission Local &#8211; October 2011</title>
		<link>/mission-local-october-2011/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 20:47:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Advocacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disabled]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mission Local]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Transportation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco State]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Transportation Gaps]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/?p=486</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss experiences the travails of a wheelchair rider on San Francisco public transit. Read The Story Here.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ralf Hotchkiss experiences the travails of a wheelchair rider on San Francisco public transit. <a href="http://missionlocal.org/2010/12/wheelchair-commute/">Read The Story Here.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simplified Strength Testing of Manual Wheelchairs</title>
		<link>/simplified-strength-testing-of-manual-wheelchairs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 23:15:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Easy Tests]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ISO Standards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Strength Testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/simplified-strength-testing-of-manual-wheelchairs/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Many small manufacturers of wheelchairs throughout the world&#8217;s developing countries do not have the resources and technical background to test their products for safety and durability. This paper suggests some essential tests which they can easily perform. The tests are based on fifteen years of experience with the Whirlwind type wheelchairs (which are manufactured and [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;">Many small manufacturers of wheelchairs throughout the world&#8217;s developing countries do not have the resources and technical background to test their products for safety and durability. This paper suggests some essential tests which they can easily perform. The tests are based on fifteen years of experience with the Whirlwind type wheelchairs (which are manufactured and used in developing countries), and on the ISO International Standard for Wheelchairs.</span></p>
<p><em>The paper is intended for use by manufacturers in developing countries who are working to improve wheelchair quality.</em></p>
<p><span style="color: #33cccc;"><strong>Background<br />
</strong></span><br />
There are many small to medium size wheelchair manufacturing shops throughout the developing world. In order to successfully market their chairs and serve their customers these manufacturers must provide chairs that are safe, durable, and good performers, and that are producible at affordable prices. This is an enormous challenge where money and materials are very limited. Although many wheelchair designer-mechanics demonstrate a high degree of skill and innovation in building chairs with available materials and tools, they often lack the background &#8212; either educationally or experientially &#8212; to evaluate their designs for safety and durability.</p>
<p>In recent years, a standard for evaluating &#8220;Western&#8221; wheelchairs has been established. It is the ISO International Standard for Wheelchairs, dated 1997 (1,2). (Previously, it was the similar ANSI/RESNA Wheelchair Standards.) These extensive Standards cover many subjects including: A uniform description of the basic seating dimensions of chairs so that consumers and health workers can accurately place orders; ways of determining tipping stability; minimal strength requirements to assure that the chair will not bend or break due to occasional high forces; and standard methods for testing long term durability where the chair is subjected to the equivalent of a lifetime of riding on rough surfaces and being dropped.</p>
<p>There are several facilities in the United States and Europe equipped to perform the tests (3). Ideally, manufacturers in developing countries should submit sample chairs for testing at one of these facilities. However, the cost of transportation and testing is often prohibitive</p>
<p><span style="color: #33cccc;"><strong>Problem Statement<br />
</strong></span><br />
Manufacturers in developing countries need simplified standards for testing their chairs. The testing methods, and minimum specified values, need to be appropriate for their testing capabilities, and their customers&#8217; riding environments. They need to include at least the tests essential to preventing catastrophic or serious functional failures.</p>
<p><span style="color: #33cccc;"><strong>Tests and Testing Method<br />
</strong></span><br />
Fortunately, the following essential strength tests can be performed by manufacturers using simple equipment and procedures. However, the durability tests, and some of the impact tests, specified in the ISO Standard require complex machines that small manufacturers cannot afford. The issue of durability will be covered later under Results and Discussion.</p>
<p>The tests, testing methods and minimum values have been developed by Ralf Hotchkiss (see Acknowledgements), and others, during the more than fifteen years history of Whirlwind-type wheelchairs. They are based on mechanical analysis, laboratory testing to ISO Standard, and extensive field testing by Ralf Hotchkiss and other riders. They found that a chair that passes these simple static or impact force tests is likely to pass the ISO tests. More importantly, it will also survive active use in rugged Third World riding conditions.</p>
<p>The diagram below shows the static and impact strength test forces a wheelchair of any design should withstand without breaking or sustaining permanent structural deformation. Tests which are in addition to those in the ISO International Standard for Wheelchairs, Part 8, or that have more demanding test values, are marked with an &#8220;*&#8221;. The rest are similar, but not necessarily identical, to those in the ISO Standard. Some test load values are followed by an &#8220;e&#8221; to indicate they are estimates of dynamic values. The related Paragraphs in the ISO Standard are in brackets.</p>
<p><strong><em>A description of each test follows its minimum test value.</em></strong></p>
<p>All the tests can be performed using a tape measure, large square (e.g., a wood or metal sheet with a square corner), spring scale, and a lever-arm made of strong pipe for measuring moments. For impact velocities, the tester can practice propelling the chair at 1.5 meters per second by, say, learning to traverse 12 meters in 8 seconds &#8212; a fast walking speed.</p>
<p>The lettered arrows (vectors) on the diagram show the direction and point of application on the test forces. A 91 Kg (200 lbm) active adult rider (either a dummy or willing person with a weight in their lap) is assumed.</p>
<p>To check for permanent deformations, before-and-after test measurements should be made using the tape to measure the distance from:</p>
<p>&#8211; Rear wheel-to-rear wheel at the front and rear (toe-in or toe-out). Better, back the chair against a flat wall. Use a large square and tape to measure perpendicularity of each rear wheel to the wall.</p>
<p>&#8211; Rear wheel-to-rear wheel at the top and bottom (camber). Better, set the chair on a flat surface and use the square and tape to measure the perpendicularity of each rear wheel.</p>
<p>&#8211; Caster axle to a rear-most point on the bottom of the each side frame. Measure when the casters are in the rolling-straight ahead position.</p>
<p>&#8211; Foot rest mounting points on the side frames to rearward points on the frames.</p>
<p>&#8211; Side-to-side between side frames at the foot rest mounting points, caster pivot bearing barrels, rear of bottom frame, and push handles, and between the front and rear of the seat tubes.</p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test Values and Descriptions</strong><br />
The order in which the tests are generally listed is determined by the clockwise progression of the lettered force vectors around the diagram. Please note that this is not necessarily the order in which the tests should be performed. </span></p>
<p>* &#8211; Indicates tests which are either in addition to or have more demanding test values than those in the ISO wheelchair standards, part 8.<br />
e &#8211; Indicates estimated values of dynamic forces.<br />
[Px.x] &#8211; Indicates related ISO standards paragraph number.</p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><br />
<strong>Test A, Downward Force on Footrests</strong><br />
1,000 N (225 lbf)[P8.5] &#8212; Force of rider&#8217;s leg pushing, or a &#8220;hitchhiker&#8221; standing, on Footrest. Test by holding the chair so the Footrest is parallel to the ground. Stand on it. Test both footrests if there are two.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test A</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test B*, Footrest Rolling Impact</strong><br />
1,800e N (400e lbf)[P9.6] &#8212; Impact force on one footrest or front of chair running into a solid object. Test by hitting a solid step at 1.5 m/sec (4.8 ft/sec) &#8212; a typical rolling speed, at about 90 degrees and 45 degrees. Test both sides.<br />
<strong><br />
Test B</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test C*, Caster Wheel Rolling Impact</strong><br />
1,800e N (400e lbf)[P9.5] &#8212; Peak force when one Caster Wheel with a soft rubber or pneumatic tire impacts a solid step. Test as for B except a 7 cm (3 inch) thick block is against the curb. This tests both the caster fork and casterwheel. Impact each caster wheel at about </span><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;">90 degrees and 45 degrees</span><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"> to the block.<br />
<strong><br />
</strong></span><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test C</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test D*, Caster Force Bending Strength</strong><br />
195e N-M (140e lbf-ft) &#8212; Moment on a Caster Fork due to C. Component test using a vise and lever-tube over the stem. About 40 mm (1.5 in) of the fork should extend above the vise.<br />
<strong><br />
Test D</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test E*, Wheelie Drop Off Inclined Curb</strong><br />
950e N (200e lbf) &#8212; Approximate sideways force on a rear wheel when doing a wheelie off a 18 cm (7 in) step, with the chair tipped sideways 5degrees, pneumatic tires on rear wheels, or rolling off a level step at an angle so that the rear wheels don&#8217;t hit simultaneously. Test by doing a wheelie off an inclined plane. It is also, the approximate force that a well-spoked 24 inch rear wheel should withstand without collapsing. </span></p>
<p><strong>Test E</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test F*, Rear Axle and Mount Bending Strength</strong><br />
280e N-M (200e lbf-ft) &#8212; Moment on Rear Axle due to E. Component test using a lever-tube over the axle while the side frame is held securely against a vertical reference surface.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test F</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test G*, Upward Force on Push Handles</strong><br />
1,140 N (250 lbf)[P8.10] &#8212; Lifting force on Push Handle when pulling chair up a 18 cm (7 in) stair with one hand. Test by doing so.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test G</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test H, Handgrip Attachment</strong><br />
1,000 N (225 lbf)[P8.7] &#8212; Rearward pulling force on Handgrip during G &#8211; difficult to test. Use a good rubber/plastic-to-metal-to-glue and skip testing.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test I*, Inward Force on Seat and Seatback Tubes</strong><br />
280e N-M (200e lbf-ft) &#8212; Moment on Folding Mechanism or Frame Cross Members when doing a wheelie off a 18 cm (7 in) step. It is best to test a complete loaded wheelchair by doing a wheelie off a step as in tests E and L. </span></p>
<p>For a frame assembly component test lay the chair on its side and squeeze the push handles together with the force necessary to cause the specified moment about the axle position.<br />
<strong><br />
Test I</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test J*, Seat Back Tube Bending Strength</strong><br />
610e N (135e lbf) &#8212; Pulling force of Seat Back fabric on top of Seat Back Tubes during test I. Do not test since this is redundant with Test I.<br />
<strong><br />
Test J</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test K*, Downward Force on Armrests</strong><br />
1,140 N (250 lbf)[P8.4] &#8212; Rider&#8217;s hand force on armrest during a pressure relief &#8220;push up&#8221;, or when boosting up to sit on the armrest to reach high. Test by applying load to armrest.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test K</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test L*, Wheelie Drop Off Level Curb</strong><br />
2,670e N (600e lbf) &#8212; Distributed force on the seat and seatback during wheelie off a 18 cm (7 in) step so that both rear wheels hit simultaneously. </span></p>
<p><strong>Test L</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test M*, Frame Twisting Strength</strong><br />
Twisting moment on frame cross members when only two diagonal wheels are supporting the wheelchair on rough ground. Test with rider seated, tester holds one footrest down while lifting the opposite side-frame with force of 355 N (80 lbf).</span></p>
<p><strong>Test M</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test N, Upward Force on Footrests</strong><br />
440 N (100 lbf) [P8.9] &#8212; Upward force on non-folding footrest. Folding or removable footrest must fold or remove at less than 44 N (10 lbf) applied at the free end.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test N</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test O, Upward Force on Armrests<br />
</strong>895 N (200 lbf) [P8.8] &#8212; Upward force on Armrest. If the armrest swings away or is removable, this must occur at less than 90N (20 lbf).</span></p>
<p><strong>Test O</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><strong>Test P, Handling Drop Test</strong><br />
1m (39in), empty &#8212; Impact during handling. Drop from the height on to each wheel when opened and folded.</span></p>
<p><strong>Test P</strong></p>
<p><strong>Results of employing the tests</strong><br />
The Whirlwind II design wheelchair passes these tests. Two such chairs were tested to, and passed, the ISO Standard tests, including the minimum 200,000 cycles on the two-drum durability tests [P10.4], and 6,666 cycle horizontal 50 mm (2 inch) drop test [P10.5]. In addition, thousands of Whirlwind chairs have been built to the established specifications, and are withstanding rigorous riding throughout the world. This attests to these tests being appropriate.</p>
<p>Therefore, passing the above static strength and impact tests is a good indicator of a chair&#8217;s ability to also pass the ISO Standard durability tests.</p>
<p><strong>Discussion</strong><br />
It is recognized that passing the above strength and impact tests does not directly test fatigue failure of the structural materials or joints. For that reason it is recommended that chairs be built of materials that don&#8217;t become brittle with repeated flexing, and any welds or brazed joints be of high quality.</p>
<p>For example, the Whirlwind chair uses malleable (mild or low- carbon) steel for the frame and other mechanical parts. This steel experiences minimal work-hardening when flexed well below its elastic stress limit. Also, when parts are inadvertently over loaded, they will bend rather than break, thus, avoiding a catastrophic safety hazard. (For example, 16mm (5/8&#8243;) diameter low-carbon steel axle bolts are used.) Also, it is generally braze-welded (gas-welded with brass) because the steel at the joints has less tendency to become brittle, and a broken weld can be easily and reliably welded by local bicycle repair person.</p>
<p>The Whirlwind chairs have the design features needed by a large segment of the wheelchair riding public in developing countries. That is, they are designed for countries where the chairs will be used in both city and village environments where rough riding conditions exist. Also, the materials and techniques used to manufacture and repair the Whirlwinds are appropriate for these countries.</p>
<p>There are many good wheelchair designs, besides the Whirlwind, being manufactured. Also, shops trained to manufacture the Whirlwind often modify the design to meet requirements important to them or their customers. It is recommended that all current and future designs and modifications be strength and impact tested as suggested in this paper. Doing so should help improve the quality of wheelchairs.</p>
<p><strong>References </strong><br />
1. &#8220;ISO International Standards for Wheelchairs (Final Draft), ISO/FDIS 7176-8, Part 8, Requirements and test methods for static, impact and fatigue strengths&#8221;, Copyright ISO 1997.</p>
<p>Available from:</p>
<p>American National Standards Institute<br />
13th Floor<br />
11 West 42nd St<br />
New York, NY 10036<br />
Attn: Customer Service<br />
Ph:212/642-4900<br />
Telfax: 212/398-0023<br />
e-mail: info@ansi.org,<br />
WWW: http://www.ansi.org/</p>
<p>or</p>
<p>RESNA<br />
1700 N. Moore Street,<br />
Suite 1540<br />
Arlington, VA 22209<br />
Ph 703/524-6686<br />
WWW: http/www.resna.org (Contact Persons/Publication)</p>
<p>2. Peter Axelson, MSME, A Guide to Wheelchair Selection, How to<br />
use the ANSI/RESNA Wheelchair Standards to Buy a Wheelchair,<br />
Beneficial Designs Inc.<br />
2240 Meridian Blvd, Suite C<br />
Minden, NV 89423-8628<br />
775.783.8822 ph<br />
775.783.8823 fax<br />
<span style="color: navy; font-family: Arial; text-decoration: underline;">mail at beneficialdesigns.com</span><br />
<span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><br />
3. Peter Axelson, MSME, List of Wheelchair Testing Facilities (an<br />
informal, unpublished list of addresses and test<br />
capabilities)</span></p>
<p><strong>Acknowledgements </strong><br />
The information contained in this paper is primarily the results of tireless efforts and experience of Ralf Hotchkiss on behalf of people who need wheelchairs throughout the world. He is Technical Director of:<br />
<span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;">Whirlwind Wheelchair International<br />
SFSU<br />
1600<br />
Holloway Ave.<br />
San Francisco, CA 94132,<br />
(415)338-7734.</span></p>
<p>The author is also grateful to Peter Axelson,MSME, Beneficial Designs, Inc.; and to Rory Cooper, Ph D., and Brad Lawrence, B.S., Human Engineering Research Laboratories, University of Pittsburgh, for critiquing draft descriptions of these tests, and the latter for testing Whirlwind chairs to the ISO Standards.</p>
<p>Note: This paper first appeared in RESNA 1996 Proceedings, Pages 414-416. This revision includes corrections, comments, and changes that reflect the current testing practice of Whirlwind Wheelchair International (formally, Wheeled Mobility Center). We intend to publish a simplified version for dissemination to wheelchair builders worldwide. It will use diagrams and require minimal English comprehension.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
