<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/bob-incerti/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 21:56:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Staff Receive Honorary Paul Harris Rotarian Awards</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-staff-receive-honorary-paul-harris-rotarian-awards/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 21:58:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Awards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bob Incerti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fair Oaks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iquitos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marc Krizack]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Harris Award]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peru]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rotary Club]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider Distribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sacramento]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-staff-receive-honorary-paul-harris-rotarian-awards/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In December, Whirlwind&#8217;s Bob Incerti and Marc Krizack traveled with a team of Rotarians from Sacramento, CA to Iquitos, Peru to distribute 174 RoughRiders that were purchased with funds raised through a combined effort of 14 Sacramento area Rotary clubs.  The team of 9 included a retired emergency room doctor and a physical therapist.  The experience gave [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In December, Whirlwind&#8217;s Bob Incerti and Marc Krizack traveled with a team of Rotarians from Sacramento, CA to Iquitos, Peru to distribute 174 RoughRiders that were purchased with funds raised through a combined effort of 14 Sacramento area Rotary clubs.  The team of 9 included a retired emergency room doctor and a physical therapist.  The experience gave Whirlwind valuable feedback on small ways that the chairs could be improved to make them easier to assemble in the field.  Bob and Marc learned that Rotarians have found the formula for making the world a better place and having a good time while doing it.</p>
<p>For their efforts, Bob and Marc were honored with the <em>Paul Harris Award</em> by the Fair Oaks, CA Rotary Club on January 28th.  The Paul Harris Award is reserved for those who &#8220;<em>have made a significant contribution to advance world understanding, goodwill, and peace through the improvement of health, the support of education, and the alleviation of poverty</em>&#8220;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Donate to Help Veterans</title>
		<link>/donate-to-help-veterans/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 19:29:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bob Incerti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/donate-to-help-veterans/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You can now make a donation and designate it for our VA Program. Whirlwind will make RoughRiders available to disabled veterans to test and provide valuable feedback through Veterans Administration (VA) hospitals around the country.   Donate Here Your donation of $800 will cover the cost of one RoughRider® for a veteran and a second [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="BasicParagraph">You can now make a donation and designate it for our VA Program. Whirlwind will make RoughRiders available to disabled veterans to test and provide valuable feedback through Veterans Administration (VA) hospitals around the country.   <a href="http://whirlwindwheelchair.squarespace.com/donate/">Donate Here</a></p>
<p class="BasicParagraph">Your donation of $800 will cover the cost of one RoughRider<strong><sup>®</sup></strong> for a veteran <em>and</em> a second RoughRider for someone in the developing world who otherwise could not afford one. Whirlwind will work with VA hospitals to identify well-matched recipients. We expect that the RoughRider will be well received, leading to VA purchases. And, by providing greater access to off-pavement adventures where most conventional wheelchairs cannot go, the RoughRider will open up more opportunities for veterans.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-984" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/Bob-Africa-72dpi-rgb.jpg" alt="Bob Incerti, Whirlwind's SF Operations Manager" width="185" height="249" /><br />
<strong>Bob Incerti</strong><br />
<strong> Whirlwind&#8217;s SF Operations Manager</strong></p>
<p>As Bob Incerti, a Vietnam vet and Whirlwind’s San Francisco Operations Manager, puts it, “Returning to civilian life from the military is challenging. Returning with fewer abilities than you went in with makes the challenge harder. Having the right equipment can help veterans meet that challenge.”</p>
<p class="BasicParagraph">“There are many wheelchair options—light, agile chairs for smooth surfaces, special chairs for various sports—that allow amazing participation. I often explain the RoughRider by saying, if I were to walk down a dirt road to a cabin in the woods with a road bike in one hand and a mountain bike in the other, the person in the cabin wouldn’t have to know anything about bikes to know that the mountain bike was more suited to their area.”</p>
<p class="BasicParagraph">“I think of the RoughRider as the mountain bike of wheelchairs, allowing folks to get further down the road, where the fishing gets good and the woods are quiet.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
