<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/press-coverage/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 03:31:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Candidate for mayor travels in his wheelchair in search of change in Paraguay</title>
		<link>/candidate-for-mayor-travels-in-his-wheelchair-in-search-of-change-in-paraguay/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:29:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://whirlwind.local/?p=9573</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the candidates for mayor of this district, despite his physical disability that prevents him from walking. He goes out in wheelchairs to visit the neighborhoods and companies to present his proposal and convince his fellow citizens to opt for change to achieve local development. This is Elvio Isidro Portillo Rojas, who launched his [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One of the candidates for mayor of this district, despite his physical disability that prevents him from walking. He goes out in wheelchairs to visit the neighborhoods and companies to present his proposal and convince his fellow citizens to opt for change to achieve local development.</p>



<p>This is Elvio Isidro Portillo Rojas, who launched his candidacy for mayor for the Tebicuarymiense Renovation Movement (MRT). The candidate for mayor, who as a child suffered from infantile paralysis that left him in wheelchairs, said physical difficulty did not prevent him from going to school, to college and he persevered until completing the career of Bachelor of Accounting Sciences at the Catholic University of Ciudad del East. He now wants to put himself at the service of his community, Portillo Rojas said.</p>



<p>He is an independent candidate of the MTR and proposes to the citizens to govern with transparency and citizen participation. He assured that he will give priority to education, health, public works, assistance to producers, support to sports clubs.</p>



<p>Portillo Rojas said that his candidacy arose through the conviction that his friends gave him, who are young professionals from different political parties in the municipality. That same group, he suggested creating an independent political movement, which can bring together the largest number of residents, to work exclusively for the district of Tebicuarymí.</p>



<p>He added that he wants to be mayor to serve and not to serve himself. “This small town has long been abandoned. The current administrators of the Municipality do not dedicate enough time to their community and almost all social assistance is politicized” he said. He said that the neighboring roads of the companies are totally neglected. The producers need technical assistance to work, the health post needs to accompany them with supplies and medicines. He specifically intends to build a laboratory and biochemicals can be obtained from the local Health Center. He does his political campaign by moving around the neighborhoods in his wheelchair. In the local companies he arrives by car or someone offers to him and they go around. The candidate visits house by house where he distributes the brochures that indicate his government proposals and the instructions on how to vote and the people receive him and listen to his proposals. The candidate for mayor is the father of nine children, he completed his primary studies at School No. 277 Santa Rosa. He then studied at the Carlos Antonio López National School, until the 5th year. He finished his secondary studies at the Dr. José Gaspar Rodríguez de Francia Regional Education Center in Ciudad del Este. Later he studied at the Catholic University of Ciudad del Este. He was an official at Itaipu Binational, where he got a job at the Communication Center. After fulfilling the required seniority and fully fulfilling his assigned duties at the Itaipu Electricity Binational, he retired and is now proposing to be the next mayor of this district.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image alignwide size-full"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/elvio-tour.jpeg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="720" height="525" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/elvio-tour.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-9575" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/elvio-tour.jpeg 720w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/elvio-tour-300x219.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/elvio-tour-500x365.jpeg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></a><figcaption><em>Encouraged by the young people, the candidate for mayor Elvio Isidro Portillo Rojas, goes out to tour the neighborhoods and companies in a wheelchair&nbsp;</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>In the sports field, he was president of the Tebicuarymí Sport Cañero Club on more than one occasion and in 2019 he was the champion president of the Tebicuarymiense Soccer League. In 1999, it enabled the Cañaveral FM Community Radio, which at the time was the only means of communication in the area, the waves of communication from the capital&#8217;s radio stations barely reached it, in 2010 it stopped working due to the economic crisis that also affected him. His participation in the political sphere is done out of a vocation to serve the community that saw him born and to whom he wants to repay with an honest and transparent administration, Portillo Rojas stressed.</p>



<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.abc.com.py/nacionales/2021/09/25/candidato-a-intendente-recorre-en-su-silla-de-ruedas-en-busca-del-cambio-en-tebycuary-mi/">Originally reported by <strong>Editorial AZETA S.A</strong></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PBS Frontline World &#8211; June 2009</title>
		<link>/pbs-frontline-world-june-2009/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 20:31:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PBS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vietnam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheels of Change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/?p=466</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[PBS Frontline World covered Whirlwind in June 2009 in a piece called &#8220;Wheels of Change.&#8221; The story focuses on Whirlwind&#8217;s RoughRider wheelchair manufactured in Vietnam.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PBS Frontline World covered Whirlwind in June 2009 in a piece called &#8220;Wheels of Change.&#8221; The story focuses on Whirlwind&#8217;s RoughRider wheelchair manufactured in Vietnam. </p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/U1JML0We6zI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Boy Scout gives back to others with help from his RoughRider</title>
		<link>/boy-scout-gives-back-to-others-with-help-from-his-roughrider/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Boy Scouts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[documentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Giving Back]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Jamboree]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Boy Project]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wes Forgey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Will Krajewski]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/boy-scout-gives-back-to-others-with-help-from-his-roughrider/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The main goal here at Whirlwind is to help people go where they want.  In Will Krajewski&#8217;s case this meant going with his Boy Scout troop to the  Boy Scouts of America National Jamboree, an event that only happens every four years.  Watch this incredible documentary below showing Will at the Jamboree motivating his troop [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The main goal here at Whirlwind is to help people go where they want.  In Will Krajewski&#8217;s case this meant going with his Boy Scout troop to the  Boy Scouts of America National Jamboree, an event that only happens every four years.  Watch this incredible documentary below showing Will at the Jamboree motivating his troop and striving to help others.  This is an amazing story and we are sincerely blown away by Will&#8217;s strength and motivation.  We would like to thank WIll Krajewski and Scoutmaster Wes Forgey for sharing their story, as well as The Boy Project for putting together such a beautifully made short documenting it all.  Keep up the good work guys!</p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/as0fyZuyVrQ?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Transcription for this video: <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Boy-Scout-gives-back-to-others-with-help-from-his-RoughRider.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i> Boy Scout gives back to others with help from his RoughRider</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>His RoughRider Allows Ironside To Go Anywhere</title>
		<link>/his-roughrider-allows-ironside-to-go-anywhere/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 21:44:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[All-Terrain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Golden Globe Award Nominee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ironside]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pilot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/his-roughrider-allows-ironside-to-go-anywhere/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whirlwind Wheelchair’s RoughRider® will be used by actor Blair Underwood, Golden Globe Award nominee, in the pilot episode of NBC’s remake of IRONSIDE. The reboot is highly anticipated given the original’s success. The drama series is about a recently disabled homicide cop, Robert Ironside.  The show, now available to pre-screen on Hulu.com, is scheduled to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-2.jpg"><br />
</a><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1130 " src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-2.jpg" alt="Actor Blair Underwood, Golden Globe Award Nominee" width="203" height="258" /></a>Whirlwind Wheelchair’s RoughRider® will be used by actor Blair Underwood, Golden Globe Award nominee, in the pilot episode of NBC’s remake of <a href="http://www.nbc.com/ironside/">IRONSIDE</a>. The reboot is highly anticipated given the original’s success. The drama series is about a recently disabled homicide cop, Robert Ironside.  The show, now available to pre-screen on <a href="http://www.hulu.com/watch/530916">Hulu.com</a>, is scheduled to air Wednesday, October 2<sup>nd</sup> at 10 pm, follows the wheelchair-riding detective as he leads a hand-picked team of “specialist” crime solvers.<br />
Looking at the original Ironside wheelchair, it’s interesting to see how far wheelchair technology and style have progressed. <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-Composite-72dpi-rgb-300x1711.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1167 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-Composite-72dpi-rgb-300x1711.jpg" alt="Actor Blair Underwood, Golden Globe Award Nominee" width="456" height="170" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-Composite-72dpi-rgb-300x1711.jpg 456w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Ironside-Composite-72dpi-rgb-300x1711-300x112.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" /></a>Ironside’s new wheelchair, the RoughRider, is both stylish and active. The RoughRider’s rugged design and ability to go anywhere fits perfectly with Ironside’s determination to go where he has to go.</p>
<p>Checking out the shows’<a href="https://www.facebook.com/NBCIronside"> Facebook page,</a> we’re excited to see that the RoughRider’s sleek and sporty contours give both a bold and confident look to the rider; while its super-durable frame has even helped the show’s film crew use it for anchoring large cameras for close-up scenes.</p>
<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.hulu.com/watch/530916">RoughRider </a>today!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Wheelchairs Brings More Joy To Camp Joy</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-wheelchairs-brings-more-joy-to-camp-joy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 18:07:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[accessibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Camp Joy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[campers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cincinnati Children's Hospital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spina Bifida Camp Joy program]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-wheelchairs-brings-more-joy-to-camp-joy/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Baylee, a camper of the youth with Spina Bifida Camp Joy program, with Paige&#8217;s Princess Foundation Fundraisers, who made the RoughRiders possible.Camp Joy is now more accessible to a variety of campers thanks to the addition of the Whirlwind RoughRider wheelchair.  Camp Joy, located in Clarksville, Ohio, is an independent, non-profit organization that specializes in [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span class="thumbnail-caption" style="width: 650px;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-1136 alignleft" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Camp-Joy-with-Paiges-Princess-with-camper-300x221.jpg" alt="Camp+Joy+with+Paiges+Princess+with+camper" width="455" height="335" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Camp-Joy-with-Paiges-Princess-with-camper-300x221.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Camp-Joy-with-Paiges-Princess-with-camper-500x368.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Camp-Joy-with-Paiges-Princess-with-camper-220x161.jpg 220w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Camp-Joy-with-Paiges-Princess-with-camper.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" />Baylee, a camper of the youth with Spina Bifida Camp Joy program, with Paige&#8217;s Princess Foundation Fundraisers, who made the RoughRiders possible.</span><a href="http://www.camp-joy.org/">Camp Joy</a> is now more accessible to a variety of campers thanks to the addition of the Whirlwind RoughRider wheelchair.  Camp Joy, located in Clarksville, Ohio, is an independent, non-profit organization that specializes in the advancement of youth and adults from all backgrounds.  Last month Camp Joy bought two of Whirlwind’s RoughRider all-terrain wheelchairs with funds donated from <a href="http://paigesprincessrun.com/">Paige’s Princess Foundation</a>.  The new RoughRiders help campers who use wheelchairs to access more areas of the camp.  According to Gunner Blackmore, the development manager at Camp Joy, “the chairs are going great.”  One camper tried the RoughRider out upon arrival to Camp Joy and loved it so much her father ended up putting her regular wheelchair back in the car.  She continued to use the RoughRider for the duration of her stay.  With the help of the RoughRider, the campers who use wheelchairs can more easily access the graveled and wooded areas of the camp that would be difficult to navigate in a traditional wheelchair.  According to Gunner, the camp is “working on improving the path down to the water” along with other parts of the camp with the hopes to make the camp’s facilities accessible to all campers.  So far, the two RoughRiders that were purchased have been beneficial to many campers including the <a href="http://www.sbccincy.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=cms.page&amp;id=1038">Spina Bifida camp</a>, Amputee Coalition participants, and the <a href="http://www.cincinnatichildrens.org/default/">Cincinnati Children’s Hospital</a> campers.</p>
<p>We at Whirlwind Wheelchair are delighted to see campers getting good use out of the RoughRiders.  We would like to thank Camp Joy and Paige’s Princess Foundation and look forward to hearing from them in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri at TEDx Ubud</title>
		<link>/sri-at-tedx-ubud/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 19:16:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tedx Ubud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ubud]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/sri-at-tedx-ubud/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back this spring we let you know Sri Lestari was going to travel from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike for made it to TEDx Ubud.  Sri just shared with us the video of her time at TEDx.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back this spring we let you know Sri Lestari was going to travel from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike for made it to TEDx Ubud.  Sri just shared with us the video of her time at TEDx.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/73zCEWpFEu4?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="460" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Findings and Recommendations from Whilrwind’s Assistive Technology Research on the Navajo Reservation</title>
		<link>/findings-and-recommendations-from-whilrwinds-assistive-technology-research-on-the-navajo-reservation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 23:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[accessibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Assistive Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[awareness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kim D. Reisinger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[major survey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Navajo Nation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Navajo Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ph.D.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quality of life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[support]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind's Assistive Technology Research]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/findings-and-recommendations-from-whilrwinds-assistive-technology-research-on-the-navajo-reservation/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Kim D. Reisinger, Ph.D, director of Whirlwind&#8217;s Assistive Technology Research (ATR) Division,  recently concluded a major survey research project on the awareness of, access to, and acquisition of low-cost, high-quality Assistive Technology (AT) devices and services on the Navajo Nation.  The research was funded by a grant from the National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1108" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1108" style="width: 368px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1108" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011-300x225.jpg" alt="Kim at the Canyon de Chelly" width="368" height="276" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011-500x375.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Kim-12042011-1024x768.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px" /></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1108" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Kim at the Canyon de Chelly</em></figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Kim D. Reisinger, Ph.D, director of Whirlwind&#8217;s Assistive Technology Research (ATR) Division,  recently concluded a major survey research project on the awareness of, access to, and acquisition of low-cost, high-quality Assistive Technology (AT) devices and services on the Navajo Nation.  The research was funded by a grant from the National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research   (NIDRR).   Check out the full article that appeared in The Navajo Post on February 14th below.</p>
<p><strong>Navajo Nation Looks to Help the Disabled with Better Mobility and Access</strong></p>
<p><em>As published in The Navajo Post on 2/14/13</em></p>
<p><strong>WINDOW ROCK –</strong> A two year project is being completed by the assistive technology research division of San Francisco State University’s Whirlwind Wheelchair International.</p>
<p>On Feb 8, Navajo lawmakers received the report of the results and the research itself.</p>
<p>According to Jerome Clark, he said the study showed, Navajo individuals with disabilities feel further disabled by a lack of accommodating infrastructure on the Navajo Nation, which they say limits their participation in daily life, and affects their roles, activities, relationships, and emotions.</p>
<p>The study is titled, Evaluation of Provision of Wheelchairs, Prosthetics and Orthotics, Hearing Aids, Vision Aids and Communication Aids on the Navajo Nation. The principle investigator of the study Kim D. Reisinger, Ph. D. said a few of the research project’s goals were to “assess the awareness of, access to, and acquisition of low-cost, high-quality AT devices and services on the Navajo reservation.”</p>
<p>Reisinger also said that participants are frustrated, discouraged, and disheartened by the inability to use their homes in safe and functional ways,” citing the absence of ramps, safety equipment such as handrails, and inaccessible spaces inside their homes.</p>
<p>Overall, there is a “general lack of awareness on what disability is, what it means, and how AT devices can improve lives,” Reisinger said, adding that participants held a general feeling of not being understood by society.</p>
<p>Participants provided recommendations to help individuals with disabilities attain an enhanced quality of life on the Navajo Nation.</p>
<p>Among the recommendations mentioned were: improving community-wide disability awareness; training local personnel to install and repair ramps, rails, and other modifications to improve accessibility; establishing a mobile service and repair unit for assistive technology devices; and investigating and redefining roles that community health representatives can play in supporting people with disabilities.</p>
<p>Council Delegate Charles Damon,II (Bááháálí, Chichiltah, Manuelito, Tsé Łichíí’), thanked Reisinger for pointing out the challenges that Navajo individuals with disabilities face, as it resounded with his own observations and with what he has heard directly from this affected population on the reservation.</p>
<p>Delegate Damon said, “Thank you for bringing to the surface the sentiments of the Navajo people on this topic. We are aware of most of the things you brought to our attention, but what we need to do is get together with individuals to provide education on optimizing use of their assistive devices.”</p>
<p>The committee has held recent discussions with the Navajo Nation Division of General Services to perform the necessary modifications to increase accessibility of governmental buildings for individuals with disabilities, said Council Delegate Jonathan Hale (Oak Springs, St. Michaels), committee chair.</p>
<p>“We need to consider the inclusion of accessibility features in future developments, but right now the Nation is facing financial constraints due to the upcoming impacts of the federal sequester,” said Delegate Hale to Riesinger. “However, moving forward, we will use your research to address the issues and concerns with area health providers.”</p>
<p>The committee plans to follow-up with leadership from the Navajo Division of Health and health care providers to develop policies that will address needs and factors identified in the research project by individuals with disabilities on the Navajo Nation.</p>
<p>Additionally, Delegate Hale stated he and the committee would like for the Division of General Services to begin looking at how they can implement governmental building modifications across the Navajo Nation to will comply with codes mandating that buildings be accessible to individuals with disabilities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years</title>
		<link>/i-havent-tipped-once-in-the-10-years/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 19:50:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[KGO radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ralf Hotchkiss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Francisco]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tip Resistant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchair]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/i-havent-tipped-once-in-the-10-years/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; Whirlwind’s co-founder, Ralf Hotchkiss was interviewed in December by San Francisco’s KGO radio. Check out the audio clip and find out why he hasn’t tipped forward out of his RoughRider’s® in ten years! Transcription for this video: I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uMtWLhIqs7s?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Whirlwind’s co-founder, Ralf Hotchkiss was interviewed in December by San Francisco’s KGO radio.<br />
Check out the audio clip and find out why he hasn’t tipped forward out of his RoughRider’s® in ten years!</p>
<p><strong>Transcription for this video</strong>: <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/I-Haven’t-Tipped-Once-in-the-10-Years.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i>I Haven’t Tipped Once in the 10 Years</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair Joins GivingTuesday Efforts</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-wheelchair-joins-givingtuesday-efforts/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2012 01:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Giving Tuesday]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inaugural Event]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spinal Cord Injury]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudardo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Survivor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yogyakarta]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-wheelchair-joins-givingtuesday-efforts/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Before this June, Sudardo, a 48-year old spinal cord injury survivor from Yogyakarta, Indonesia, was limited to his village and a few surrounding villages due to his difficulty in traveling.  In June, he received his RoughRider® and now collects 15 bags a week and provide for his wife, son and two daughters.  His RoughRider also [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1399" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1399" style="width: 318px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1399" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023-300x200.jpg" alt="“My RoughRider is very special to me.” - Sudardo" width="318" height="212" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023-500x333.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC_0023-1024x683.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 318px) 100vw, 318px" /></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1399" class="wp-caption-text"><em>“My RoughRider is very special to me.”</em> &#8211; Sudardo</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Before this June, Sudardo, a 48-year old spinal cord injury survivor from Yogyakarta, Indonesia, was limited to his village and a few surrounding villages due to his difficulty in traveling.  In June, he received his RoughRider® and now collects 15 bags a week and provide for his wife, son and two daughters.  His RoughRider also allows him travel all the way to the nearby town’s center that is a few kilometers each way.</p>
<p>Whirlwind Wheelchair is joining the Giving Tuesday (Nov. 27<sup>th</sup>) inaugural efforts.  This holiday season, for each group of 20 people who give $10 each, a wheelchair user in Indonesia or Haiti will be able to more easily navigate his or her city or village, contribute to the family household and more fully participate in society.  Please contribute today by selecting to donate to the Giving Tuesday Program.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.givingtuesday.org/"><img decoding="async" src="http://www.unfoundation.org/assets/images/gt-badge.png" alt="World Homeless Day" border="0" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>“I feel so much freedom, I love it!”</title>
		<link>/i-feel-so-much-freedom-i-love-it/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 21:25:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Press Coverage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US WheelChair Rider]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/i-feel-so-much-freedom-i-love-it/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meet Brian, one of Whirlwind Wheelchair’s first US customers.  Living in San Francisco, hear why Brian loves his RoughRider.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Meet Brian, one of Whirlwind Wheelchair’s first US customers.  Living in San Francisco, hear why Brian loves his RoughRider.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tw1V2VEXEAk?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
