<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/ucp-wheels-for-humanity/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 22:06:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Will Sri Lestari Reach TEDx Ubud on Her Modified Motorbike?</title>
		<link>/will-sri-lestari-reach-tedx-ubud-on-her-modified-motorbike/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 22:23:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disabled]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspiration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[model]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modified motorbike]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[paraplegic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social workers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tedx Ubud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UCP Wheels for Humanity]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/will-sri-lestari-reach-tedx-ubud-on-her-modified-motorbike/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last week we shared a photo of Sri Lestari, a social worker who is employed by a Whirlwind partner, UCP Wheels for Humanity, in Yogyakarta, Indonesia.  We found out after our post that she has been asked to speak at the TEDx Ubud conference on June 1st.   Sri is hoping to make her trip to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.indiegogo.com/project/365537/widget" width="224px" height="486px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Last week we shared a photo of Sri Lestari, a social worker who is employed by a Whirlwind partner, <a href="http://www.ucpwfh.org/">UCP Wheels for Humanity</a>, in Yogyakarta, Indonesia.  We found out after our post that she has been asked to speak at the<a href="http://tedxubud.com/"> TEDx Ubud</a> conference on June 1st.   Sri is hoping to make her trip to Ubud a much richer experience by traveling from Jakarta to Ubud on her modified motorbike increase awareness and share her experiences with others in the disabled community along the way.</p>
<p>I asked Sri what motivated her to make this trip (almost 750 miles) on motorbike. She responded with the following:</p>
<p><em>“Since I work in UCP Wheels for Humanity 2009, I visit more disable who just stay at home.  They are happy when they see me, because I am disabled, I am a women and I can work. I really want to share my experience how can be life independence and healthy as disabled (paraplegic).<br />
“The campaign really important because disabled in Indonesia still difficult to get out from their houses because no access, especially for public transportation.  My live change since I have modified motorcycle.</em></p>
<p>“Most people didn’t trust me when I told them that I am paraplegia, they surprise I can live independently, go everywhere by myself on the modified motorcycle and can work. When I do social assessment with the paraplegic, at the beginning they don’t believe me, after I talk deeply about paraplegic they are more open, when I told them that I can ride the modified motorcycle they smiling, I am so happy can make them smiling, after that they will contact me regularly and more deeply asking how can be independent specially for our daily live and get a job and they invite me to visit them with my motorcycle.</p>
<p>“Each time there are new paraplegic in my hometown some friends will tell me to visit them, mostly family who has disabled very happy when I visit them. Some of them  are desperate  to support the disabled  to have more spirit, because the disabled  will said that you are not feel what I am feeling, but when I talk to them they won’t refuse me, because I just like them.</p>
<p>“Some Mom who has children with disability said that, they want they children can be like me, even be diffable person but still can work.</p>
<p>“I am happy because I can work n earn money, so I can do home visit to my paraplegia friends in my home town or Yogyakarta in the weekend, share my experience n give them motivation.</p>
<p>“But I also want to share out of my home town and out of Yogyakarta, so that why I really more supported to do the trip.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wheelchairs and New Production in Indonesia</title>
		<link>/wheelchairs-and-new-production-in-indonesia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 01:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[India]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Production]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Partner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resources for Advocates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabdo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UCP Wheels for Humanity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wheelchairs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/wheelchairs-and-new-production-in-indonesia/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Indonesia is one of the poorest and most disaster prone countries in the world with tsunamis, earthquakes, and 155 volcanoes &#8211; like the Merapi volcano that swept away the village of Cangkringan last fall. According to the World Health Organization, there are 6.4 million children with disabilities in Indonesia and at least as many adults. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Indonesia is one of the poorest and most disaster prone countries in the world with tsunamis, earthquakes, and 155 volcanoes &#8211; like the Merapi volcano that swept away the village of Cangkringan last fall. According to the World Health Organization, there are 6.4 million children with disabilities in Indonesia and at least as many adults. Even though there are many schools, most kids who need a wheelchair don’t attend. Severe poverty makes a good quality wheelchair impossibly expensive. For growing kids, this means education ends early when they become too heavy for parents to carry.</div>
<div></div>
<div>In the last year, UCP Wheels for Humanity, a Whirlwind partner, has trained</div>
<div>
<figure id="attachment_1019" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1019" style="width: 343px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1019" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm.jpg" alt="Sabdo out on the road to school." width="343" height="345" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-768x773.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-500x503.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-100x100.jpg 100w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-298x300.jpg 298w, /wp-content/uploads/2011/05/sabdo_by_himself_from_friends_picture_sm-66x66.jpg 66w" sizes="(max-width: 343px) 100vw, 343px" /></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1019" class="wp-caption-text"><strong> Sabdo out on the road to school.</strong></figcaption></figure>
<p><span class="full-image-float-right ssNonEditable"><span class="thumbnail-caption" style="width: 250px;">Sabdo out on the road to school.</span></span> a small army of therapists in Yogjakarta to custom fit each wheelchair and provide all the necessary follow-up services to each recipient. Good service and better quality chairs has made a big difference. Now riders can participate in social and economic life, mothers can make it to the store and kids can make it to school.</p>
</div>
<div><strong>A rugged wheelchair and individual care can be provided for under $300, a fraction of US healthcare costs.</strong></div>
<div><strong> </strong></div>
<div>You can help change a life! For 200 wheelchair riders in Indonesia, your  donation to Whirlwind Wheelchair will make a life-changing difference and open a completely new future. Your generous donation will change children’s lives.  Your donation will help many more than just these 200 people because it will pay for tools and equipment needed to put our wheelchair into large scale production. The result will be high quality, low cost wheelchairs that will be available for thousands of riders every year. This is more than a one time donation opportunity, you are making an investment in the future. Can you send your donation today?</div>
<h3>Resources for Whirlwind Advocates:</h3>
<div>&#8211; <a href="/storage/fundraising-materials-indonesia-2011/Whirlwind Wheelchair Indonesia Project Donation Opportunity.pdf">Fundraising Appeal Letter</a> &#8211; it is ready for Advocates to print or email to friends</div>
<div>&#8211; <a href="/storage/fundraising-materials-indonesia-2011/Wheelchair Rider Stories Organizations and Project Budget.pdf">Additional Information</a> &#8211; project budget summary and additional stories about wheelchair riders.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
