<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/social-enterprise/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>A non-profit social enterprise dedicated to improving the lives of people with disabilities in the developing world while also promoting sustainable local economic development</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 22:05:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Shifts into High Gear with International Quality Standards</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-shifts-into-high-gear-with-international-quality-standards/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 20:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expansion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high volume]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[highest quality product]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indonesia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international standards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jogjakarta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mass production]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QC Systems]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social enterprise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lestari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tracking customers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind RoughRider]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[worldwide]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-shifts-into-high-gear-with-international-quality-standards/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With the 2010 Whirlwind RoughRider® on track to reach more than 20,000 riders next year, the process for ensuring that each chair is of the highest quality becomes an even greater challenge. Unlike Whirlwind’s first 25 years, it is no longer cost-competitive for one person to hand-make every RoughRider from start to finish. Now, as [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure id="attachment_1102" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1102" style="width: 449px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-1102 alignright" src="http://216.172.184.37/~ab85381/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-300x200.jpg" alt="Sri Lestari takes her nephew for a ride on her Whirlwind RoughRider® near Jogjakarta, Indonesia." width="449" height="299" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069-500x333.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sri-saturday-069.jpg 735w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1102" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Sri Lestari takes her nephew for a ride on her Whirlwind RoughRider® near Jogjakarta, Indonesia.</strong></figcaption></figure>
<p>With the 2010 Whirlwind RoughRider® on track to reach more than 20,000 riders next year, the process for ensuring that each chair is of the highest quality becomes an even greater challenge. Unlike Whirlwind’s first 25 years, it is no longer cost-competitive for one person to hand-make every RoughRider from start to finish. Now, as we expand into mass production, Whirlwind and our partners must streamline the production process to create experts in the manufacture of specific wheelchair parts and collaborate to make a great product. Whirlwind’s development of complex quality control systems is emblematic of our transition from a traditional nonprofit to a social enterprise capable of delivering unique, top quality products to tens of thousands of riders in need all over the world.</p>
<p class="Normaltext">Whirlwind is working with our overseas manufacturing facilities, ensuring that design specifications, change processes, and production methods yield the highest quality product possible. To achieve this, the Whirlwind tech team has developed formal processes for controlling quality, managing design changes, and effectively tracking customer complaints to continually improve the RoughRider. International standards guide Whirlwind and our producer-partners to create and implement QC systems effective in managing high-volume, industrial manufacturing applications around the world.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whirlwind Wheelchair Project with CIR in Afghanistan</title>
		<link>/whirlwind-wheelchair-project-with-cir-in-afghanistan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel Curtis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2005 18:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afghanistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for International Rehabilitation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[distribution strategy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kabul]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kabul Orthopedic Organization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social enterprise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Training of the Handicapped Trust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wheelchair kits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whirlwind]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workshop]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Workshop for Rehabilitation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.websitesbycreation.com/whirlwind/whirlwind-wheelchair-project-with-cir-in-afghanistan/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whirlwind and the Center for International Rehabilitation conducted a six-day training workshop in Kabul, Afghanistan, in June 2005 that focused on skills such as wheelchair assembly and repair, fitting and user assessment. The goal of this project was to test a distribution strategy that combined central fabrication with local assembly, fitting and delivery. During the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whirlwind and the Center for International Rehabilitation conducted a six-day training workshop in Kabul, Afghanistan, in June 2005 that focused on skills such as wheelchair assembly and repair, fitting and user assessment. The goal of this project was to test a distribution strategy that combined central fabrication with local assembly, fitting and delivery. During the initial phase, wheelchair kits were manufactured by Workshop for Rehabilitation and Training of the Handicapped Trust (or WORTH Trust, a social enterprise with the goal of employing people with disabilities), in a regional facility in Katpadi, India. The kits were then delivered to Afghanistan, where they were assembled, distributed and maintained through the cooperation of a local nongovernmental organization, the Kabul Orthopedic Organization.</p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Nog5sYtHvjI?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" width="100%" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Transcription for this video: <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Whirlwind-Wheelchair-Project-with-CIR-in-Afghanistan.pdf"><i class="fa fa-download " ></i> Whirlwind Wheelchair Project with CIR in Afghanistan</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
